即係主席。
噉我哋開會啦嚇，人數夠啦。
咁咧，首先咧，以前嘅第一項咧，就係上次嘅逐業事項咧，有一個環表畀大家睇嘅，就唔需要今日討論。即係大家我嚟誒參考下上次兩次嘅誒，我哋要跟進嘅問題咧，佢就逐一就答翻我哋。秘書多謝秘書處咧就。
就整一個表，令我哋比較清晰啲去睇到我哋問嗰啲咩問題，佢又答過啲乜嘢。裏邊咧就誒，仲有啲咧係未曾回應嘅咧，咁等佢一回應咧就會補充落個表度嘅。喺度咧，我哋好多謝西九管理局。
誒嘅朋友同埋民政事務局嘅出席嘅同事咧，出席今日嘅會議。
噉啊，今日咧主要有兩項咧，誒三項咧重要嘅嘢講。第一咧就係Amers嘅規劃同埋發展啦，同埋西九文化區嘅公園發展啦，以及咧西九文化區計劃建築工程嘅開展。
嚇！前開始前。
啊！佢嘅管理同埋使用嘅情況。
好啦，噉啊，再次歡迎大家出席今日嘅會議啊！
咁而家咧，我哋第二項嘅議程咧，就係就Amplus嘅規劃同埋發展嘅提供最新資料。咁咧就誒政府文件應該都係畀咗大家啦。尋日嚇，咁請大家咧誒請啊誒民政事務局有冇誒發言？
好啊，唔該。
主席，誒西九管理局咧就曾經喺去年咧四月向呢一個小組委員會咧就展述咗M加嘅願景同埋發展情況。誒至到今日咧就M加已經喺呢一個建立專業團隊、建立館藏、博物館誒建築物嘅設計同埋拓展觀眾等多方面咧就取得進展。
M家咧已經將佢嘅購藏嘅政策啦，同埋佢購置咗同埋獲贈嘅藏品嘅內容咧，係上載去到管理局嘅網頁，係畀市民去參閲嘅。咁M家咧為咗培育我哋本地嘅人才咧，佢係推出咗一個即係擴大咗規模嘅實習計劃。唯有至於喺呢一個領域發
展嘅年青人咧，就提供咗參與今年咧六月至到十一月舉行嘅威尼斯雙年展嘅學習機會。此外咧，今年年初咧，佢亦都推推出咗呢一個導賞義工計劃咧。呢兩項計劃咧，都獲得超過一千七百份嘅申請。呢個咧顯示咧，我哋香港人咧對於參與M加嘅興趣咧已經。
係誒，正在增加㗎啦。
管理局咧就提交咗文件啦，向小組委員會去匯報M家嘅最新進展。而家咧，我就請誒西九文化管理局行政總裁連立智先生同埋M家嘅行政總監李立偉博士咧，向各位介紹有關嘅內容。誒，多謝。好，請啦，主席。
Thanks, Mr. Chairman. Good morning, members of the subcommittee. I've got with me today Dr. Lars Netfer, the director of M+, and I'd like him to take us through the.
那係一些關鍵議題，我們在談論，我們非常樂意回應有關M Plus的問題。我們處於非常興奮的階段，旅程中，陪審團將在5月討論提交的設計方案。
We hope to have that decision resolved over the course of the coming months. It's also an important time in terms of two major events for M Plus. The one that Dr Netfer will talk about, the inflation exhibition, which will open later this week on the West Kowloon site, which is a big public fun ente.
Entertainment exhibition, and importantly, from Hong Kong's perspective, the project that M Plus and the Art Development Council are doing to represent Hong Kong at the Venice Biennale, opening on the twenty-eight th of May. I think there's a range of other issues in the paper and specific issues.
That you would want to pick up from previous conversations, including the contribution that we've had from both Dr. Sig in terms of his collection, and increasingly an interest from the collectors of Hong Kong and other places to look at making philanthropic.
contributions to the collection for M Plus, which will be very important in being able to maintain the momentum on the project. So perhaps I could just hand over to Dr. Sieg to say some introduction. Sorry.
excuse me, Mr. Chairman, to Dr. Nitford to say a few words of introduction.
Thank you very much, Chairman. Well, as stated in a paper, basically the M Plus organisation are working on four things in parallel continuously. One is of course building a team, because without a team you can't do anything, and the M Plus team is basically.
21 members of staff, but with seven more members in the pipeline, in various stages of recruitment. So we will hit probably around 30 staff members in the beginning of of the autumn, which is badly needed since the three other tasks that we have.
focus on is of course building a collection, which is a major major undertaking in terms of research and market research, scientific and and cultural research, negotiations and so forth. So that's a big task. The other, which is of course coming closer and closer, because we're in the middle of
The architecture competition right now is building a building, and we will of course act as a client, as as a use end user client in that entire design process, and it will be a very demanding task if.
We aim at getting this building absolutely right. Building it from inside out, as we've always said, not just building a building and then then seeing what we should have in it, but actually making it fit for its purpose. And then thirdly, of course, the entire big task of building audiences and building capacity.
and nurturing talents in in Hong Kong, and as
As CEO Michael Lynch said, I mean we do this through our exhibition programmes. Now, next upcoming is the inflation exhibition, which I expect will reach large audiences in Hong Kong. It happens on the site, more or less on the site of the future M Plus and the park.
And it's a big, big project with with which has a lot of fun in it also, and is really would work also for families and children to visit. Hoping for good weather since it's outdoors.
We also, as as was mentioned, work in Venice with the Venice Biennial.
我諗，more，maybe，even，more，importantly，we，do，a，number，of，of，public，public，introductions，the，serious，M+，matters，public，programs，the，public，forums，where，we，talk，and，meet，the，public，and，meet，stakeholders，and，talk，about，everything，we，do，and，try，to。
As much transparency as ever possible, and thirdly, of course, the project to to build talent, to build to nurture talents, to build build future sort of staff for M plus and for similar institutions around Hong Kong through various types of training programmes, internship programmes and.
So forth. So these are the strands we're working on, and it requires full force ahead. And I think I can say after two and a half years in the post that.
The results we see are, we're actually a little bit ahead of schedule according to the plans we established about two years ago, and things have been going really well. We've had very good results in all areas, but it's a lot of work. Thank you very much, Chairman. Okay.多謝大家。
份。
如果冇咧，咁到我哋誒委員咧，大家誒即係提提問。
嚇！請提問嘅舉手，因為今日嘅議程都比較多咧，噉我哋會每次咧就係就四分鐘連問連答。
嚇，謝偉全嚇，一路舉手啦嚇，噉我問住。
叫住先啦嚇，謝偉全先。好，多謝主席。就誒，我想問一問咧，喺嗰個文件四嗰度咧，有講嗰個員工招聘咧，咁其中有十名咧來自香港咧。其實我想了解下咧，基本上咧，即係誒嚟自香港同埋非嚟自香港咧，喺個工作。
性質上咧，係主要有冇咩分別，或者主要從事乜嘢咧？噉啊，呢個呢個第一個問題。
噉啊，第二個問題咧，就我想都係講翻，即係嗰個評審嗰個誒分數嗰個誒計法咧，即係誒。
關於戲曲中心嗰陣時，我哋都係已經係誒，都我諗我哋都表達咗意見啦。咁喺呢個ampers嗰方面咧，其實即係有冇檢討下，即係上次戲曲中心嗰個誒關於設計嗰個評審方面咧，就有冇地方可？
可以係調整或者改善咧嚇，唔該，主席。O.K.誒，邊位答啊？誒，民政事務局啊。
你話，Mr.林。
誒關於嗰個員工嗰個誒，我請阿阿Doctor Lee誒誒about the staff，誒what is the job nature of the staff we could from Hong Kong？Would you please誒？
佢是。
Yes.
I think from the outset we were aware of the fact that we wouldn't be able to find all types of expertise in Hong Kong, but that we would move towards when the museum opens and for the future that we would sort of nurture talent and build talent in the areas where there's that where we don't have sufficient experience in Hong Kong.
At the present, roughly, and that's been the model since since we set out, is that at least half the team should be from Hong Kong, and it's good if about a quarter could be from the region, from other parts of nearer Asia, I should say, and then the occasional individual, maybe.
25% or so coming from elsewhere, where we need specific types of expertise. There is no difference in the team between between Hong Kong staff and staff from other parts of of Asia. We have the the head of education comes from Hong Kong, the senior
新任策展人來自中國大陸，的首席 registrar 或 registrar， which is a very sort of very expert type of job， comes from Spain。 But all in all, there is no sense of hierarchy or difference other than we go.
just out to try to find the best expertise we can ever find anywhere in the world to build a great team. Over time, we hope that we will be able to transfer, say, from the red star, transfer the knowledge from her over to more junior staff that we're hiring from Hong Kong, so we can build a pool of expertise within.
在香港，在這非常特別的領域，在其中沒有任何正式的教育。在全世界，這些是通常在職業中學習，在主要機構中，然後轉移到其他機構。
咁關於嗰個誒？
嗰個計劃，嗰個點樣啊？
Second question, Mr. Chairman, I'm happy to take that on. Clearly, the competition and the assessment criteria we provided are the assessment criteria that were entered into, approved by the board last year before the competition went out. We're not in a position to change the criteria part way through.
The competition, but as you will have seen from some of the discussion following the board meeting last week, the chairman has made it very clear that looking at value for money, looking at the cost issues, is an overriding interest for the organisation at this point in terms of the individual projects, but also looking.
the total budget of it. I think the the one point I would make is that the rules of the Hong Kong IA, in line with international competitions, rule, we have injected the idea of cost and value for money into the competition. Under their rules.
They don't have rules for the the cost issue. That the competition is meant to, with each of the competitors providing their QS.
to be able to provide their estimates, we have an independent QS. We have independent costings of the project as it's developed from inception in in two when the the project was funded in two thousand and eight. But we are very conscious of the issue and we'll be putting significant.
emphasis on our discussions as we move into. Okay, Mr. Lin, 我諗佢哋會即係繼續會誒問呢啲問題㗎啦，係嘛？已經過咗時間，希望咧，因為時間唔夠咧，希望問同埋答咧都比較精簡同埋誒對住嗰個問題去回答啦。跟住何秀蘭。
唔該，主席。誒，我哋做博物館咧，嗰個館藏係會先天不足嘅。一，我哋又唔係帝國主義通道去掠奪咗好多人哋嘅文化藏品翻嚟，我哋香港冇噉樣做過。第二咧，就係香港自己本土，我哋以往亦都唔係話有。
好多藝術家留落一啲好嘅文化遺產畀我哋，但係館藏咧唔係一定要擺一啲誒百年嘅鎮山寶喺度去畀人睇，亦都可以係一個同誒現代生活大家結連係一個互動嘅過程。
係等大家睇一到誒一啲現代生活、本土過去一啲好基本嘅誒歷史係可以擺到出嚟噉，所以咧嗰個策展人嘅獨立自主係非常之重要嘅喺我哋香港呢個咁新嘅博物館咧，人才比。
管藏可能係更加重要，咁是故我哋要確保呢啲策展人嗰個獨立自主，同埋佢哋嗰個表達方式。噉我瞭解到咧喺第十二段嗰度咧，我哋舊年年中就買咗一批誒藝術品。
係現代中國重要嘅作品，咁裏邊咧，誒，我據理解係包括咗幾件艾美美嘅作品添，咁其實。
喺誒西九行政總裁初上任嚟嘅時候咧，我哋都已經咪問過Mr. Lynch。
誒，當面對即係萬一有來自各方嘅壓力嘅時候，可唔可以負起確保策展人、西九管理局嘅工作人員一個藝術上邊嘅獨立自主？噉我就想問一問，誒而家呢個機制係？
點樣確保佢哋嘅獨立自主咧？誒，我希望艾美美嘅作品喺西九管理局唔係一個爭議啦。咁而呢幾件作品係可以幾時攞出嚟喺香港展出咧？
冇嘢啦，唔使理。
嗯。
To answer question number one about the independence of the curators, and I appreciate this question. I think it's a very important one. I don't think you can run a successful cultural institution without independence and freedom and clear freedom of expression. And I think that.
most of the key members of the curatorial team would not stay in post if they felt that there was any type of regulation in their ways of working. So I think it's self-regulating. Actually, we have recruited a number of curators who easily could have jobs anywhere in the world, even also.
of those who are from from Hong Kong because of their expertise and their standing professionally and they would never risk their standing by by being subject to any type of censorship or other regulation and I the first time I was in Ledgeco two years ago I received the
Same answer, and I said that for me this is also the way forward. If there were any signs of regulations or decrease of freedom of expression, I mean, I would probably not stay in post. I mean, it's as simple as that. If my arguments don't go through.
在terms of showing the collection and of course.
And not unimportant part of that collection are works by Ai Weiwei, for example, and many many other important mainland artists. The plan is that we will make the first presentation during two thousand and fifteen, when the arts pavilion is up and running, and we plan to show.
The story of Chinese contemporary art, the 1980s, 1990s and the 2000s, in three different sections there, as a first taste of this fantastic collection. Thank you. 我希望香港唔好有政治壓。我諗咧就已經聽得到㗎啦。可以令到呢批國際專才留喺香港。我聽到㗎啦嚇，已經過咗。
時間噉啊！頭先未有人跟咧，我就跟咗有兩條問題，我都係跟進何秀蘭嘅問題。我想問下，而家你策展人請咗幾多咧？你頭先個團隊話有二三十人，而家你請咗幾多咧？第一噉，你如果未請齊人，你咁早就走去採購、收藏呢啲噉嘅嘅時候，你係咪？
喺一個好先天不足嘅情況底下去做進行呢啲咁危險嘅事情。
第二、第二、第三咧，就係話。
誒在採採購嘅時候咧，好多世界嘅一流嘅博物館採購嘅時候咧，都會係主動去自己挑選自己嘅藏嘅少藏品嘅，即使係人哋送畀。
呢個博物館，但係我哋好似咧缺乏依個勇氣去挑選呢啲噉嘅藏品，就任任由人哋畀乜你就要乜，咁呢樣嘢係唔係違反咗嗰個策展人嗰個獨立性，同埋佢自己嗰個誒獨立自主嗰個方法咧？噉係咪依依方面咧，我哋做得非常？
啲藥係任人牽著個鼻嚟走咧。
第二個大嘅問題咧，就係關於嗰個展館比賽。頭先已經答咗咧，就話根本上就冇可能改啦，因為誒嗰個成本效益咧已經係喺舊年已經開咗個設計別㗎啦。而家我哋改唔到，中途改唔到。噉我想問下你預計Amplus會係翻係話畀我哋聽，你會攞幾多錢嚟？
興建Empress嘅。
嚇！因為我哋唔係提款機啊，就算我哋係提款機啊，我哋都有錢㗎嘛。咁唔係任你撳嘅喎。噉我想兩個問題答一答，好嘛？
Mr. Lind, please. Okay, let me take let me take the last one first, Mr. Chairman. Clearly, what we're asking we're not asking for, and I think we've made it clear that once we've gone through the competition and gone through the costing process, we'll then be in a position to have that discussion with Ledgeco. And as I understand.
Understand that scheduled for later in July. In regard to the the question of the curators and the collection.
嗯。
We have to have a collection in the within M Plus, and all of those decisions are made by the acquisition committee of M Plus, which is comprised of advice from Lars and the and the curators within the team. But those decisions are.
即係唔係拆紙人決定，It's not by creator. It by it's by adviser. You say it.
Well, the authority is given to the acquisition committee by the board of Westcarlun, so that's the way we have to make the decisions about acquiring work. And clearly, of the eight hundred and sixty-seven pieces of work that have been acquired for the M Plus collection, outside those of the Sig collection.
那些決定已經由採購委員會作出，而700幅作品是由香港藝術家創作。
可會有The list of the name list of the advisers？
Yes, you can have the committee. The committee is chaired by Dr Victor Low, who chairs the museum committee, and it comprises Claire Soo, the head of the Asian Art Archive, David Pong, Nansen Shear, and
兩誒，show we show we。O.K.，我諗你會後畀我哋啦，好唔好？咁但係我都好質疑點解你急得咁緊要要去買嘢？佢個creator都個團隊都未成立好，你就趕住去買嘢，老急咩？你根本冇地方剪㗎嘛，係嘛？Well, no, the we we certainly the.
works we are acquiring are related to the parts of the collection that we're building up on. As soon as we have the new curators in specific areas like moving image and contemporary culture, that's when we will be acquiring。我想問啦，我問政局啦，你哋有冇一個procedure話畀佢聽，有個程序話畀佢聽？
點樣去採購？佢而家係咪已經跨越咗個程序啊？誒誒，西九管理局咧係有誒誒傾研究過，同埋係通過咗誒一套整體嘅誒嗰個購藏嗰個政策嘅。咁亦都係包括裏邊嘅程序。咁呢啲程序咧就誒，亦都有諮詢過廉政公署嗰個意見。
同埋咧，誒喺誒誒呢個董事局下嗰個博物館誒諮詢委員會嘅委員嘅意見去制定嘅。咁所以誒，今一次誒嗰個誒誒館藏嗰個收購咧，亦都係按照呢一套嘅誒館藏購藏嘅政策去誒進行嘅。我諗會後你畀個程序我哋睇睇啦，好嘛？好。
下一位，陳婉霞。多謝主席。
誒，我我我我噉樣，我會問曬啲問題之後咧，我會再舉第二次手嘅。我驚我未必有第二次。我諗你誒，我噉我問曬先啦。我我我對第一個員工，我有質疑嘅。
國際嘅定義點解咁快話香港部分唔得咧？即係我覺得你話如果你個leader係有呢個經驗嘅，當然我強調類似水墨畫嗰啲咧就唔使啦，中國大把即係類似呢啲。但係如果你話就算國際嘅，我當咗你而家要有個國際嘅，你咪leader用一個啦，何須請咁多個咧？你全部full曬啊嘛！
即係我就覺得國際嘅定義，我哋講笑，我咪識英文先叫國際咧。而家香港文化界就質疑緊呢個問題啊嘛。噉我自己國際就呢個我想問嘅。第二個咧就話個設計未有，你咁快主要問嗰個構藏噉，我跟住即係話噉你咪到時構藏好多嘢咧，嗰個建建築費又好大咧，咁呢個亦都我關心嘅。
即係我覺得兩者之間，我特別覺得政府由於你民政呢部分咧，我擔心。即係到底香港要使呢筆錢嘅時候咧，你做呢個位置，你到起嘅咩位咧？有冇一啲好專業嘅support住你睇翻呢啲嘢咧？主席，我連起三個問題，唔該。好，即係答啦，盡快答。
因為。
嗯。
Should I? Yes. Mr. Buttigieg. First of all, first of all, the question of why we have outside experts because.
operating and make.
Operating a large museum.
作為我們設立的，是very，它是一個專業任務，而我們沒有長傳統或主要博物館，隨時間而建立的這個能力，因此在早期階段，我們需要帶來一些類型的專業，對於沒有正式培訓，從其他部分的世界，它是一個。
minority of the team, and I think over time they will transfer their knowledge to the benefit of.
of of the Hong Kong team and the Hong Kong public and that we will have this expertise in Hong Kong, but I think that we're given the task to create something that actually has world class standard, and then we have to do it in the way that we find proper.
It's not about English or not English, and actually, as a matter of fact, some some of the the overseas experts speak speak Chinese, so it's not a language matter, and I think everybody is aware of that also.
嗯。
When it comes to to the expertise of choosing the collection, I think just a year ago we there were doubts about our ability to big build large enough collection.我未講揀藏品，我哋嘅設計個個個博物館未做，噉你跟住買曬咁多藏品，咁到時你話誒我買咗咁多嘢。
大啲啦噉樣，而家你仲係進行設計，未進行一個比賽㗎嘛？我問緊呢個問題。
嗯。
Well, the the whole idea with this project, and as it was outlined by the museum advisory group in two thousand six two thousand eight, was that we should build a museum from inside out. That we should not repeat the mistake that's often made. That first you build a building, and then you start thinking about what should go in it. The
兩節都識講。冇意思啊！又冇時間。所以，由於我冇時間，我要講咧，呢個係觀點嘅角度啫。我覺得你咁講有你嘅道理，但我嘅講法亦都係個道理。而且我仲想誒話畀政府聽，使香港我哋好多畫廊啲都好。
好專業，好有國際經驗嘅。對啲成個政府構思，而家你成個家就畀咗人哋當嘅，你變咗文化界出邊啲人就算嘈緊啦。即係喺呢個過程當中，點樣本地嘅就算當咗我係誒亞太區嘅，我哋都係國際部分啊嘛。即係啲意見好大嘅，主席，我覺得我問題好清楚。另外個設計費問題，我擔心。
而家未嚟嘅個Empress嗰個。
誒可唔可以畀到個設計費？你估計係幾多啊，Mr. Lee？
Can you guess? Can you guess the?
the course of the of empires.
I think I just answered that question. No, we we the the figure in the budget, no, in the CC case, no, is the only figure we have at this stage. We will obviously be providing that information to you as soon as we no have got the submissions from the the six.
Companies and and our independent QS has done that. Just going back to the the issue of local galleries, clearly we have recruited from both public and and private galleries in Hong Kong. But the issue in you have not had a contemporary art museum other in the other than in.
The private sector, and this is the first museum of that type. And so, from our point of view, we'll be looking at people from the best available expertise. Our curator from China, our curator from both Chinese. You can answer in other questions.
馬逢國，跟住，誒多謝主席。誒，我我嘅問題咧，因為我係董事會嘅成員咧，我先申報啦。咁所以好多西九嘅情況我都比較瞭解。咁有一個問題咧，我就係關於嗰個管藏嗰個誒採購嘅問題。
嗯。
我我會重點講係嗰個價格嘅問題。誒，政府有今年咧就破天荒第一次咧，就係喺預算案啱啱提出，最近都誒，聽日都仲會跌碑嘅，就係會有一個五千萬嘅撥款咧，係去採購一啲畀誒康文處嘅博物館去做進行採購。噉我覺得。
有啲奇怪嘅就係，即係政府點樣去考慮，或者西九本身點樣去面對，就係佢從來都冇一個獨立嘅預算。咁今年咧就突然間有個獨立嘅預算，咁同時咧西九亦進行緊採購。咁當然從嗰個業者嚟講咧，譬如話特別係香港嘅藝術家咧，啊突然間多咗一個大嘅預算去採購咧，對。
佢嚟講係一個好嘅，噉我我係某從代表業界嚟講，我係支持嘅。咁但係調翻轉嚟講咧，即係我又想問翻啦。譬如話從西九管理嗰個角度就話，哦，政府有呢個噉嘅採購政策，新嘅一個採購政政策出台係LCS做嘅，咁咧同西九本身進行緊嘅同共同時間進行緊嘅。
個採購會唔會產生咗啲競爭嘅狀態咧？會唔會因為咁咧，係導致到我哋喺採購上邊咧，係要負擔更加高嘅費用咧？咁事實上，由西九個出現同埋最近即係西九個管藏啊開始採購之後咧，成個藝術品市場咧已經係有一個好大嘅變化，將會。
會出現嘅好多外國嘅大嘅誒gallery或者本地嘅一啲畫誒畫廊啊，都已經係同時進行緊採購一個噉嘅新嘅現象嘅出現嘅時候，到底對未來嗰個市場嗰個影響會係點咧？即係西九自身點樣去評估，或者點樣看待呢幾樣嘢咧？咁而政府亦都同時點樣睇？
一個我哋而家有少少係我哋人為做出嚟一個一個噉嘅誒誒誒，即係市場噉。譬如話好多畫廊咧，最近嘅嘅拍賣啊，都已經係上即係有我我感覺到啲有一啲噉嘅佈署咧，就係令到嗰個價格咧係更加合理啊！即係更加合理，即係特別係一啲香港嘅作家嘅誒嘅誒。
嘅嘅嘅藏品，咁呢啲噉嘅情況，總體嚟講，西九自身點睇？政府點睇咧？唔該。
係政府，我誒首先其實咧，就想就住誒政府咧提出嗰個建議咧，係話誒額外撥款五千萬畀康文處去購藏嗰度咧，我就即係誒都想誒誒提供一啲資料嘅。咁誒首先咧，就康文處其實佢嗰個購藏嗰個政策咧，就係一早已經係定咗落嚟咧，就唔係話。
因為今次有額外五千萬咧，就去有一個新嘅購藏嘅政策。誒，因為咧，康文署下嘅博物館咧。
誒，康文署下下嘅博物館咧，誒特別係呢一個藝術嘅博物館咧，其實佢嗰個博物館本身嗰個購藏嘅政策咧，個重點咧，正正就係以香港為本位嘅藝術嗰個全面點樣去展示啊、誒研究啊，同埋係去推廣，即係向香港。咁呢一個咧。
就係已經係確立咗已久嘅一個誒購牀嘅政策嚟㗎啦。咁誒過往嚟講咧，康文署咧佢就冇一個好固定嘅誒，即係預算咧，係每一年可以係買幾多呢啲管牀噉，所以咧就變咗咧，佢哋就好唔穩定咧，就誒好多時候可能去到誒個財政年尾嗰陣時候咧，就見到啊。
係有一啲誒，可以即係都係動用嘅咁先至去買，咁變咗咧就喺一個即係誒噉嘅情況底下去購呢個管藏咧，就喺嗰個整體個策劃嗰度咧就唔係咁理想。咁所以咧，我哋就即係希望咧，去誒將來都可以係有一個充分嘅時間去策劃同埋去去喺個市場嗰度去搜購一啲適合。
嘅管牀，咁所以咧就額外撥撥咗呢一誒，即係建議撥呢一個五千萬。咁但係呢個五千萬咧，其實係冇時限嘅，因為我哋唔想話誒硬性規定康文署一定要係誒幾多年裏邊一定要用曬嗰五千萬，因為其實最重要係佢自己物識到一啲合適嘅管牀，噉就因應嗰個誒適合嗰個誒管牀咧。
咁去去進行呢一個選購嘅，咁所以咧就誒呢個五千萬咧就嗰個用意同埋嗰個出發點就係噉樣，咁而誒藝術博物館咧同埋誒西九嗰個誒誒M加嗰個博物館咧，其實佢哋一路都有好緊密嘅聯繫咧，就大家都好瞭解大家嗰個定位係點樣嘅，咁香誒香港。
自己嗰個康文署下嗰個藝術博物館咧，佢嗰個重點咧就真係聚焦喺我哋自己本地香港整體成個藝術嗰個發展咧，由佢以往到而家，同埋係一個全面係各方面去即係誒好多種唔同嘅藝術家佢嗰個特點啊，個特色係點樣？噉我哋香港自己。
呢個藝術博物館咧，係嗰個定位係噉樣嘅。而西九嗰個咧，佢就係誒一個係當代嘅，即係佢係focus喺呢一個二十世紀同埋廿一世紀啦。佢就即係以香港為出發，但係亦都會係擴展到去亞洲啊同埋世界各地嗰個當代嗰個藝術。咁所以大家都好了解，大家嗰個定位係點？
點樣噉啊？會互相配合嘅咁同埋咧，其實佢哋喺買管藏嗰陣時候咧，大家都會有溝通咧，就唔好去重複嘅，因為其實大家都係即係公共嘅資源啦。咁所以其實佢哋咧係即係即係將來一路去做嘢咧，都係可以有合作嘅嘅誒誒空間喺度。即係譬如佢哋策展嗰陣時候啊，做嗰啲誒展覽。
如果係可以用得著大家對方嗰啲管牀咧，其實佢哋係可以互借嗰啲管牀嘅。咁所以誒，我就即係誒提供個資料去到呢一度。我我夠鐘啦，其他啲問題咧，我希望就書面答覆啦。就誒民政事務局同埋西九管理局嚇，下一位咧就係蔣麗雲。
唔該，主席。啊，我有兩方面嘅問題。啊，第一個問題咧就簡單啲。嗱，我睇到咧喺第七段咧。
噉就提及到噉就係Amplas咧，就首個第一個實習計劃已經完成咗啦。噉我想知道咧，就有幾多嘅啊學員參與噉，同埋咧就完成實習之後咧，就有幾多個畢業嘅學員會繼續參與油麻地嘅支援工作。
咧噉。
噉啊，第二方面嘅問題咧，就係又係有關呢一個啊藏品㗎啦。咁其實我都想知道咧，就目前有冇一個政策，譬如話誒呢個呢個誒誒五年之內呢十六億，我諗住係會有幾多嚇，即係喺。
係係麥誒幾多錢活撥喺做香港買香港嘅誒藏品嘅？幾多係國際嘅，或者誒其他誒，或者係內地嘅，或者係其他國家嘅？即係喺呢度有冇一個政策咧？咁？
咁咧就嗯，同埋我亦都想知道咧，目前嚟講，十六億已經用咗幾多錢咧？仲剩幾多咧？唔該。好，答咗呢度先啦。
啊，多謝你。
On the first question, at the time which was one year ago, that training programme involved three interns. At the time, we only had a staff of seven, also, so we couldn't take many more interns than three. Of those, all three were first hired for another after the internship programme.
They worked for another three months on on a sort of project basis in within the M+ and at the present, one of the three has a job in M+ as an assistant curator.
誒。
As mentioned, the later internships programmes involves larger numbers of of people because we have a bigger organisation now and can with quality handle more people.
第二， on the policy for for acquisitions after a five year period. First, maybe it should be clarified that out of the one point actually one point seven billion Hong Kong dollars for the collection and collection related works or costs, only one billion is earmarked for the actual.
collection。
It's impossible to predict what percentage should be for different parts of, of say whether it should be Hong Kong art or Asian art or mainland Chinese art. Partly because we can't say how things will develop in terms of donations. Of course, the
portion of money that had to be spent on mainland Chinese contemporary art, for example, went down considerably thanks to the phenomenal donation of 1.3 billion, more than the entire acquisition budget actually, to M+。所以那那意味著我們可以 allocate more money for other areas。但係，since we are
receiving donations also from Hong Kong artists to date 13 now 12 Hong Kong artists have been giving us works also major Hong Kong artists that also makes our burden in terms of where money is spent a little bit lighter I should mention in reference to an earlier question.
That donations go through the same type of scrutiny and decision-making process as an acquisition. There is no difference in terms of that. So it's just that it's not just that anyone who wants to donate will be accepted. It's the same kind of process as with an acquisition through purchase. Thank you.
既然係噉嘅話咧，又會唔會啊？即係考慮啊？咁咧就而家，因為橫店個廠館都未起，會唔啊？即係啊啊？咁會唔會咧？就係而家積極去揾多啲人，即係捐贈嘅啊？咁咧，因為假如你捐贈好多有都夠啦。
足夠未來五年啦！噉你十六，噉你剩低嗰啲錢，你咪可以攤翻咯。
阿Tom啊，Tom啊，係嘛？
Well, in in general, in general, we'll be looking at finding ways of supporting it through philanthropic donations, sponsorship, collections being donated. But clearly, recognising the pressure on the the cost of the project, recognising the increase in construction costs, will be
Engaging with the Hong Kong community and the broader artistic community in looking at the forms of support we've we've got. I've talked about that before with Ledgeco. We're looking some issues that we've looked at. We're now focusing on the philanthropic and the sponsorship opportunities to make sure that we maximise the amount.
Money that we can contribute both to the collection, but also to deal with the cost issue.
噉你會後畀翻個誒資料我哋啦，嚇你話拎翻嚟啦，好下一位，我不如讀一讀個名先。而家第一輪咧就係劉慧卿、姚思榮、麥美娟、梁家傑就未講嘅，噉啊劉慧卿。
誒多謝主席，主席誒，首先咧我就多謝阿陳文偉博士同埋黃寶怡女士啦。琴日佢嚟我辦事處咧，就同我解釋啲嘢，噉啊，即係我哋多謝官員咧，或者係西西九啲人士多多啲同我哋解釋。噉我亦都講話最好咧，就喺委員會度清清楚楚交代咧。
呢個係最有用，但係同我哋多啲溝通，我哋係歡迎嘅。噉我就希望咧，就係即係嗰啲數咧，主席就盡快會列得清楚出嚟。誒，無論係嗰個戲曲中心又好，第二啲即係你列曬啲數出嚟，畀人睇到超支係點解，係邊樣係因為係通脹，或者因為有。
新嘅項目各樣嘢，我希望係即係當局同埋西九係盡快會噉樣做，即係畀份文件畀委員會誒，大家去睇。咁對於誒呢個Amplas主席，我係好希望咧，我哋係會畀到個空間咧，係揾到一個好出色嘅設計，因為大家都好希望一。
有啲人話：，哇！你成日話香港係國際大都會啊？點解啲啲啲啲嗰啲嗰啲誒建築物咁鬼核突㗎？點解都唔會有多啲地標式？但係我都明白咧，如果你係要有啲地標式各樣嘢，可能咧個價錢係會貴啲。
咁但係，即係我哋而家咧，我哋立法會，我所以我哋把關咧，就係要揾到個平衡。噉你上一次講個戲曲中心，亦都唔係話最貴啦。即係我哋亦都未必，即係我唔會話覺得誒，你唔使啦，淨係揀最平嗰個啦。咁亦未必咁上一次就傾就話係咪揾啲有成本效益㗎嘛？主席。
噉，琴日兩位解畀我聽咧，就話國際上咧係冇咁寫嘅，因為上一次我都問喂，咁外國都有好多比賽㗎嘛，噉佢哋係點寫嘅咧？即係唔係我哋一定跟足佢，但係我哋要參考，因為我哋都要國際嗰啲人嚟嚟參加㗎嘛。咁所以我希望佢哋好簡單講一講係點做，同埋。
咧，即係誒管理局係點樣係盡咗最大嘅努力，去令到嗰個成本係受到控制。即係而家講緊個設計嗰度啦嚇，受到控制。但係咧，亦都希望咧嗰個過程咧係會令到啲有創意啊，即係好有才華嘅人咧係願意參加，而幫到香港咧係有。
呢啲好嘅設計，我覺得呢個係好重要嘅。咁同埋而家又噏唔到個數啦，主席。即係幾時先可以畀到個數立法會咧？嗱，上一次咧馬逢國議員咧，啊佢喺咪度啦嚇，即係佢講咗啲説話係令到我哋好憂心，因為佢坐兩個位啊嘛，佢又係管理局。咁後來佢又解釋啦嘛，噉佢其實佢越幫就越忙。
我都其實都唔知後來係乜啦。佢話一定係超支㗎啦，啊最好就增加地積比嚟去去貼啦。咁又冇人惡意佢喺管理局又冇啊，呢度又冇。咁如果佢管理局啲人都咁講咧，阿主席你唔係啊嘛，我都唔係。噉我哋更加擔心咯。所以希望你哋清楚楚講畀我哋聽呢個過程係。
點樣？即係嗱，市民係想有嘅。
當然平靚正啦，梗係，但係未必得。但係如果係要要多錢嘅時候，你要解畀我哋聽㗎嘛？你淨係拎個大數嚟，哇超支咗百分百啦噉樣，噉啊梗係唔掂啦，主席。哦，主席掂嘅，係佢。噉啊，請誒解釋下，又有時間。
Well, the process for the design choosing is that we are using an international jury of which you have the details of that jury. It's comprised of art experts from Hong Kong and from other parts of the world, and comprises the the chairman of the.
Museum Committee of the WKCd and the Director of M Plus, Dr Netfer, clearly the criteria that we've used are laid out. But from our point of view, the the process that we've looked at for both buildings and the process that we've outlined.
到這個委員會，我們有獨立的品質調查員看預算，對這些項目，個別的提交都是預算化的，我們有技術委員會在目前審查這些提交，我們有成本顧問看這些委員會，這個過程會繼續。
Through to the the jury sitting in May, and then continual work will go on as it goes through the development committee of the WKCD and to the board of the WKCD. So we are incredibly conscious of the issue of cost, but I have to boringly reassert.
the issue that the the major issue in regard to cost for these buildings is the fact that construction cost in Hong Kong have risen over 100% over the last four years. That includes government projects and private projects. And so clearly, that information has
已經非常廣泛地在委員會討論過。我們認識到這會對項目施加的壓力，整個項目的範圍在前進方面，我們將盡一切努力，與專員團隊、內部人員、項目團隊以及建築師和設計團隊一起。
chosen to make sure that we get a quality outcome for value for money. Chairman, they should give us the figures as soon as possible so that we understand how the thing is developing. 呃，呢就會畀你㗎啦，嚇噉啊！我哋希望喺七月十號個會議嘅討論嘅時候咧，已經有齊曬啲資料。咁咧，跟住落嚟要。
四圍。
多謝主席。
就有關提升大家對西西九嗰個文化區認識咧，報告入面提到係拓展呢個觀眾羣嘅，呢個係好事嚟嘅。我想問問咧，誒喺呢個展館未開之前咧，呢兩年咧，誒呢個有關方面咧係準備搞幾多場嘅？
嘅活動，咁誒準備同咩單位合作？
咁誒目標嗰個觀眾羣係準備有幾多，同埋嗰個費用預算係準備有幾多咧？
邊個答？
係。
Totally, we have, which is also mentioned in the paper, made a number of of programmes already. We do basically two public exhibitions annually on on on average, plus a number of talks, symposiums, public forums and so forth, and they have.
稍微不同目標，在不同時間。Sometimes the projects are very much about the sort of the local community. They happen in a local community, as with the Yamate project. The Inflation project is very much a sort of serious but still fun family project in a sense, where I think.
I think anyone from a three-year-old to to my grandmother could come and really enjoy it. And of course, we have the public forums and the M+ matters, which have attracted thousands of people who come and participate in a debate. These are the general frameworks annually, two projects per year from.
二零一五。
When we have the arts pavilion in place, that will be our base on West Kowloon. Generally, roughly, the budget for these programmes are about, as a totality, in the figures of fifteen million annually, which involves ex.
exhibitions and and other types of projects.
Thank you。O.K.，仲有冇其他補充？冇，係啊，姚。係主席，我想問咧，呢一千五百萬係誒呢兩年嘅開支咧，定係未來嘅開支啊？同埋佢嗰個觀眾羣，我聽咧都係本地為主嘅。將來有冇考慮喺旅客方面咧誒提供一啲宣傳？
使到大家對我哋西九個認識更加深刻一啲。
係邊個回答？係咪問政局？
The the target is local is local audience primarily because that's our core audience. This is the audience we would like to build and build a relationship to over time. It so happens, for example, that both this year and last year, the big projects there are big projects that happened during the time of.
The Hong Kong Art Fair or Art Basel this year, which also means that we attract actually large numbers of the world's leading art experts to come and see our projects. But it's really much more difficult to build a tourist audience because we pop up in different places, and it's very difficult to communicate to tourists.
Where to go this time or that time? It's much easier to reach the local audience. And at the end of the day, it's for the people who live and working Hong Kong. We primarily create M+. I'm sure the tourists will come because we create something that is world class. But we are here for the people of Hong Kong.
OK，阿偉。
麥美娟。
即係第一個問題都係咧，誒點解即係成日都話要喺外國先至可以揾到你哋認為係國際級或者世界級嘅人咧？即係如果頭先咧嗱，啊副秘書長就講咧話，康文署咧會同你哋係有啲咩交流合作嘅，咁即係話。
其實我哋都唔係有啲唔能夠同你哋交流嘅人啦。咁唔通康文署嗰啲人唔係咩，即係又唔係世界級咩？如果佢哋康文署嗰啲未到嘅，咁即係同你哋又唔唔能夠合作啦，係嘛？咁即係其實你講啲有啲矛盾嘅。我哋係有人嘅，OK？結都咧，頭先你講嗰啲咧，要誒要揾其他地方。
嘅人咧，即係我相信我哋香港咧，其實有好多你講contemporary arts咧，我哋香港亦都唔少，只係你有冇心機去揾佢哋出嚟啫。OK，噉啊，如果你都冇心機去揾，你梗係冇啦噉。咁另外咧就你頭先講你啲internship嘅，其實我我諗咧做呢個管咧，你請咗人。
人翻嚟，你有一個誒負責人係一個國際級之後咧，你又可以如果我哋講個誒技術轉移咧。
其實可以由嗰位嘅負責人將嗰啲知識或者技術咧，透過管理咧去畀翻一啲香港嘅本地嘅人嘅。咁但係依家如果講你冚唪唥都喺可能嘅team裏邊一半甚至大半都係外外國人嘅，或者其他你聲稱世集世界級。
啲人，咁點樣可以將嗰啲技術轉移到畀香港咧？移翻出嚟，即係你你嗰個時間咪要搞好耐，同埋究竟你有冇噉嘅心去做咧？
internship嗰樣嘢咧，你你話你培養好多實習咩咁？你點樣可以令到佢哋實習完之後可以吸納翻喺個呢個管裏邊，喺將來可以做嗰個頭先再強調嗰個技術轉移？香港以前都有嘅其他工程喺隧道咩咁？
我哋最初冇人嘅，透過技術轉移可以做到，但係而家呢個管，我哋可唔可以做到呢樣嘢咧？似乎我哋冇乜信心可以做到呢樣嘢。
第二樣嘢就真係再講一次，喺我哋香港裏邊有好多嘅藝術家可以提供佢哋嘅知識，可以同我哋嗰啲誒國聲稱國際級嘅人咧去合作嘅。只要我哋有一個負責人咧，可以同佢哋一齊合作嘅。咁但係點解你哋唔去喺嗰度盡量explore去揾？
咧噉，另外頭先你講嗰樣嘢咧，我啲擔心。你話你要揾嗰個展品，然後先至去決定嗰個設計，要inside out㗎。咁咧，你點樣去決定個budget咧？去到尾，你會唔會因為我有咁多展品，所以我要起一個館去cater，即係去去扶。
配合去迎合或者接納曬我咁多，容納曬我咁多嘅展品，最終又超過budget咧，又會會有超支咧？
你點樣去控制嗰個開支嘅預算咧？
O.K.打打。
Perhaps I'll pick up the first part of the question and then ask in terms Dr Nitford to comment. All of the jobs that we recruit people from are open to Hong Kong. Many of the a number of our employees have come from L.C.S.D. institutions, including the head of education for.
Plus, you know, from so, and LCSD and other people are able to apply. The only issue that we are applying is that we need specific expertise. So when we need an expert in Chinese contemporary art, we chose after rigorous selection procedures. P. Lee from Beijing.
因為他被國際上視為領先的專家。類似地，在設計這個非常國際化的領域上，香港，我們選擇了Eric Chan，中國裔美國人，他曾在北京和紐約工作，作為代表。但我們的焦點是提供機會給。
Hong Kong people, unless there is no specific expertise that we need to be able to build either the building, the collection or the institution. Now, I'll ask Dr. Nitford to comment because I realise the time pressure we're under.
唔好講 parti啦。Okay， just briefly on the on the internship programmes， I don't think there is any internship programme in the world where you guarantee the people who come， who are in the interns， who are interns that they will get a job。 We will try to employ as many as possible， but the good thing is that we also provide people。
有進一步training than they had before for other institutions in Hong Kong for the L.C.S.D. museums and so we broaden the pool of people with skills in Hong Kong. We're not only working with ourselves as a focus, even though we will be the big new employer of course on site. So I think that we some of the interns will get a job.
with with M plus others will end up working in other institutions, other places, and I think that's a value. We we enrich Hong Kong and the pool of expertise simply.
好啦，其他嘅嘢就一陣間先至誒，或者係書面答覆，因為我哋今日嘅啲第一輪呢個議題咧係去到十點鐘，而家都十點鐘啦，仲有兩位第一輪都未未答未問嘅，噉我哋問完咧就完結呢個議題，誒。
請副主席梁家傑。係多謝主席。主席，我就好關心嗰個管藏嘅策略，同埋嗰個策展人有冇足夠嘅誒自由空間去決定嗰個誒管藏嘅策略啦，同埋佢誒策展嘅時候係咪？
有一個自由度嗱，咁誒，我哋一直都知道咧，主席就係西呢個西九裏面嘅M plus呢個博物館咧，係有四個視覺文化範疇嘅。
咁而家據誒西九管理局今日交上嚟嘅文件咧，就有三個拆展人咧，就住其中三個時覺文化範疇咧，都正在喺度招募之中。
咁物件冇交代清楚，係咪第四個誒視覺文化範疇已經有拆遷人咧？
但係，如果喺當你有啦，咁四個之中有三個都未埋位，你已經有咁多嘅。
藏品誒買嘅有買嘅誒人哋送嘅有送嘅，噉你點樣可以誒話畀我哋聽？即係呢個策展人咧係有一個誒決定。
佢嘅館藏策略啊，同埋佢策展嘅安排啊，同埋藏品嗰個誒，佢有冇自由嘅空間咧？噉樣，即係我想知道其實係點樣啦。咁第二個問題就簡單啲嘅，就係我想問下咧。
就係而家你話呢啲藏品咧，已經係誒由一個信託準備用嗰個信託嚟到去持有咧。呢個信託已經係成立咗未咧？
個信託人係邊個咧？主席。
Mr. Lee, please.
啊。
Deputy Chairman, in regard to the trust, we are still establishing the trust as part of the conditions of gift, and that legal work will be completed in the coming months. The trustees will be a
I think that the final mechanism is that they are appointed by the chief secretary to represent the interests of the collection, and we would provide that. They haven't as yet been appointed until the legal deed is drawn up.
In terms of the curatorial team, maybe there is a need for a clarification. We do have eleven curators in post already. Eleven curators, and we have expertise in in most areas which is related to what we call visual art in different areas: Southeast Asian art, Chinese art. We have experts in.
In in Hong Kong art as well as well as in design, what we are missing mostly at the time is is is in an expert a top expert in the in the field of moving image and we need deeper expert in the case of ink art. But we definitely have a world class team.
already in place for the areas where we have made been making acquisitions, and then of course we will expand the scope when the further team members are on board. So, but thank you for your concern. Thank you。主席，我想跟一跟咧，就係誒，如果嗰個信託未成立咧，而家嗰啲誒捐贈或者購置嘅。
藏品係點樣去誒安排嘅咧？同埋誒嗰個策展嘅嗰個安排咧，將來係咪都會用一個誒，即係不排除一個藝術責任制。即係上次啊，Mr. Lee。
講過咧，將會好快係會就住點樣去誒營運每一個場館咧，就會有個拍板咧。噉係咪呢個藝術責任制亦都不排除係喺M+博物館嗰度實行咧？
你所啲。
Well, the trust will be established prior to the establishment of M Plus. I'm not sure I get the the number of the question in terms of. I'm just asking, what is happening to those artwork before the trust is established? Okay. Well, no, the the majority of the Sig work.
都還係喺一個安全的收集設施，喺我們嘅管理下，喺瑞士。一但我們有咗安全嘅設施喺香港，無論係短期或者長期，喺M+博物館嘅範圍內，呢啲作品都會返到香港。
Works that we have bought outside the Sig collection are all in secure facilities in Hong Kong. But one of the issues we're grappling with is that it is actually cheaper for us to keep the works in a Swiss facility than it is to keep them in a secure facility in Hong Kong.
O.K.，陳鑑林最後位。
主席，我有誒兩個觀察，同埋一個問題。
首先咧就係關於嗰個超支嗰個問題。啊，剛才啊，劉慧卿議員咧都問咗啦，即係當然係，即係希望誒西九管理局可以將嗰啲資料咧啊財政嘅狀況咧係話畀我哋聽。
但係，我亦都必須要講嘅咧，就係。
喺當時咧，係通過呢一條。
誒，即係財政撥款嘅時候咧，二百一十六億咧。
政府係斬釘截鐵咧，係講過好多次咧，二百一十六億係冇問題嘅。
可以建成整個西九嘅誒呢個文化區嘅。
咁所以，我哋要話畀管理局聽，同埋話畀政府聽咧，係必須要好好噉樣控制。
整個管理局而家西港文化區裏邊咧，所有建設嗰個費用。
千祈唔好出現咧一個就係使腳唔抹腳嘅情況。
同埋而家，我哋而家見到嘅整個誒安排啊，各方面嘅嘢咧，似乎都有好多甩漏嘅嘢。我哋好擔心嘅咧就係。
西角管理局以為咧。
因為而家有好多嘅所謂誒。
誒建築嘅費用啊，各方面嘅嘢係增加咗之後咧，你畀個數字我哋，將來立法會會增加撥款。我希望話畀你聽嘅就係，我哋會好審慎控制呢一個噉樣嘅開支，我哋唔會輕易。
嚇，就係會應承呢一個噉樣嘅增加個撥款，噉我希望你哋可以清楚。
第二個咧，就係關於嗰個。
展品嗰個收購嗰個問題，我哋完全尊重。
誒，你哋喺手扣嘅過程裏邊嗰個表達嘅自由。
但係表達自由咧？
佢係有個原則嘅。
我相信你哋都清楚嘅咧，就係。
逢係不雅淫褻，甚至到有政治性、有侮辱性呢一類嘅。
藝術品咧，佢係唔屬於藝術品嚟嘅。
咁必須要係好清楚，有個大嘅原則。
雖然間係表達自由，但係自由兩個字唔係突然間喺個天裏邊爆出嚟嘅。
佢係經過人去揀選嘅，每一個人。
可能都有唔同嘅政治取向。
咁所以，我會希望咧，西九管理局作為一個獨立嘅。
一個文化藝術嘅管理嘅專業人才咧，係應該要好小心嘅衡量呢樣嘢。
我哋完全無意作出任何嘅政治嘅干與，但係我希望你哋都能夠時刻記住咧。
藝術就係藝術，文化就係文化。
另外一點咧，我想問一問嘅就係。
因為而家我哋係向一位當代嘅中國嘅藝術品嘅收藏家咧。
嗰個誒希克博士。
係買咗四十七件嘅。
呢個收藏品。
佢亦都贈送咗畀我哋咧，係喺千幾份嘅啊呢個啊收藏品。我想知道一下就係。
誒點解佢可以送千一千四百幾份，但係又要賣四十七份咧？咁到底個過程係點嘅樣咧？
佢可以送成十三億噉嘅價值嘅呢個展品畀我哋。
誒點解佢仲要賣億幾一億七千幾萬畀我哋咧？咁點解唔係全部送曬咧？另外就係你哋喺揀選嘅過程裏邊咧，係點樣做法咧，主席？
可唔可以簡略答到？如果唔可以，就書面詳細答你。Now I'm I'm very happy to answer this question, and and it is a relevant question, I think, because it's not obvious.
It is a practice that when a donation like this or a transaction on this scale happens internationally, when someone gives away his or her entire life's work and collection, as in this case.
Every museum in the world is out chasing this individual, and in this case, it was Tate, it was the Metropolitan Museum, it was MoMA, it was Guggenheim. They were all trying to get this collection. I think we were also in the position that we were actually a budding museum. We did not really exist at the time when we started these.
discussions， and that was what Dr Sig asked for was a sign of commitment from any of these museums to show that actually you're you're prepared to make an effort you just offer an effort you just don't want and want everything and this is something that something that's been tried before there is a
number of precedents for this also.
The Count Giuseppe Panza in relationship to the Guggenheim Museum, Mr Anthony Dofe in relationship to Tate and the Scottish National Gallery. This is a model that's been used in similar cases, and I think that psychologically, from the donor side, he or she wants to see a sign of commitment or proper.
commitment and that's what we gave him and he gave us works worth 1.3 billion which is the envy of the entire international art world. So
It was not an easy decision to take, but I think at the end of the day, I think it was a glorious decision that that the board made actually.
主席係咪因為我哋誒，即係佢送嗰嘢畀我哋，我哋就要同佢買咧？因為經過一個咩一個揀選嘅程序？我諗咧，嗰個誒書面答覆翻我哋嗰個誒，即係程序啦，同呢位誒希克博士誒，即係大家一齊誒商，由開始商討一個簡略嘅過程。
咁同埋即係有冇透過點樣？
It's in the reverse order that we purchased one hundred. We purchased forty seven works for a value of one hundred and seventy nine million Hong Kong dollars, and he gave us one thousand four hundred and sixty seven works at a value of one point three billion Hong Kong.
I think, as it is not well understood in Hong Kong, the idea of philanthropic gifts is that the person who is giving determines the terms on which they make that gift, and then we went through the process, including approval by the West Kowloon.
board of the terms and conditions for that gift, and then you know that that's what was negotiated. I guess the issue that we would hope to be establishing in response to your question around philanthropic gifts and the sorts of things that we would get is that we would be hoping to encourage.
Major philanthropists in Hong Kong to be supporting these institutions in whatever way they can by either making donations. But we are dependent on them deciding to do that. I can't really ask Lee Kau Sing to give all of his money to West Kowloon, but I would have no hesitation in.
asking him to give some of his money to Westcalle好嘛？咁至於誒嗰個procedure點樣咧，嗰個程序點樣咧，你都可以説明話翻畀我哋聽。我哋下一個議程，唔好意思啊，誒美分議員，因為誒我哋講到最後兩位，因為今日已經即係超咗依個依個議題超咗十五分鐘啦嚇，唔好意思。噉你睇下下一個議題啊，做。
啲舉手，下個議題咧就係關於誒。
西九誒個文化公園嘅發展情況，誒民政局有冇咩誒？
介紹。
九嘅公園咧，將會喺市中心開拓一個嶄新嘅綠化地帶，為音樂、舞蹈、劇場、藝術展覽同埋其他户外嘅文化節目提供一個活力誒充滿活力氣息嘅場地。西九文化管理局咧，而家現正進入咗呢一個評審入圍設誒設計隊伍提交嘅提誒投標文。
件嘅階段，與此同時咧，為咗配合公園嘅第一期嘅落成咧，管理局咧現正着手去擬誒草擬嗰個附例嘅工作，亦都計劃咧喺呢一個附例嘅內容係具備嘅時候咧，係盡快去諮詢呢一個委員會嘅。噉就住今天嘅會議咧，誒管理局亦都係提交咗文件。誒而家我請西九文
文化管理局行政總裁連立仔先生咧，向各位去介紹。
好，主席。
Thanks, Mr. Chairman. Well, the park is the third major piece of the project that is underway at the moment. We have commenced some initial works in terms of site investigation, the establishment of the tree nursery, but we are also continuing to do major events, including.
在M+ inflation event and a number of other events on the site, we will be making the decision to who will be the designers of the park over the course of the next coming weeks. And we are also in response to the discussion that we had last year with Ledco, working.
on resolving the bylaws for the longer term for the park, that works going on at the moment, and clearly as the deputy secretary has said, we will bring those draft bylaws back to Ledgeco for further discussion. We will also discuss those draft bylaws.
with the district council, and we will use the consultation panel under its new chairman to seek public views and to be able to make sure that the bylaws reflect the intentions that we have publicly put out that the park is that they are not excessively restrictive, they will not in
禁hibit enjoyment of the 23 hectares of this public space, and I expect Sid Ho will be very happy with them by the time that they are resolved.
就冇。
噉啊！請大家舉手提問。我諗，我諗附例嗰度咧，遲啲咧佢交咗上嚟咧，我哋先詳細傾好嘛？因為咧，大家都應該集，我建議啊，大家都係集中傾下咧嗰個設計啊、建築啊等等有關呢個硬件嗰個問題，即係誒嚇。咁請大家提問。
而家舉咗手有梁美芬、陳婉嫻、何秀蘭嚇，咁一路問一路舉手啦。誒，每人都係四分鐘連問連答。梁美芬先，係主席誒，就住嗰個誒公園草坪嗰個設計咧，我都係想跟進下咧，就係誒，我哋好早咧就一直提希望。
望咧就係多啲林蔭大道啦，接而而呢個誒呢啲嘅休憩地區咧，將來都接連到附近嘅一啲誒誒市區嚇。咁咧呢一方面咧，我睇下嗰個落實程度係點，同埋係咪真係可以係林蔭小徑或者大道咧？我哋開頭就用林蔭大道嘅，後屘都。
都即係係將佢咧，就係無論佢係臨蔭大道也好，臨蔭小徑也好，呢一方面咧係誒現在進展係點？接連附近上次講嘅，譬如誒話惡士電站啊噉樣，呢啲路會唔會通嘅咧？定係純粹係喺公園內裏邊嘅誒步行徑咁？第二咧就係單車。
勁啦，會唔會有呢一方面嘅考慮咧？咁第三咧就係誒喺嗰個雕塑同埋裝置嗰方面咧，其實同剛才嗰個議題頭先同事討論到嘅咧都相關，即係有冇一個公眾參與喺度咧？當你哋選擇，即係譬如我哋誒去誒外國一啲城市咧。
佢哋都會擺擺唔同嘅雕塑，咁有啲甚至係某啲喺當地出生嘅名設計家嘅一啲特色。
肖像噉樣，咁但係誒，我哋喺誒選擇呢啲擺放物嘅時候，能唔能夠其實大家都有一個選擇喺度？咁喺公眾佢都會可能誒剔嚇，可以佢唔係唔誒誒，你有一個嘅誒調查，或者你有一啲嘅畀佢哋選擇，咁可能。
分數高啲，原來誒大家中意多啲嘅，你就會擺喺嗰度，因為你相對嚟講，可能係好長期擺喺嗰度，而即係其實欣賞嘅都係公眾，亦都可能會更加代表咧係我哋誒嘅一個誒特色。
咁咧就誒，我亦都注意到咧，就係話喺誒，即係似乎我一定都順便講埋啦。喺誒吸納當地人才嗰方面咧，你哋係一路係話咧有一個困難。誒呢啲困難，你冇分析過咧，其實點樣可以係誒戰勝佢咧，係令到咧其實。
誒，無論大大細細嘅呢啲工程項目或者設計項目咧，都可以誒令到當地一啲人才嚇，包括誒設計嘅人才啦，誒甚至佢熟悉環保工程嘅人才啦，佢都可以參與咧。
Okay.
Thank you, Ms. Lung, for the question. The lawn will be there. Will be many thousands of trees in the park. But that the decision that we're about to make about the park design will determine the configuration of the space. What we have laid down is the things we want within the park. In regard to the
Art in the park. That will be a responsibility of Dr Netfer's team to be both commissioning works to go into the park for long term works. If you look at some of the Millennium Park in Chicago or the Olympic Park in London, where major pieces of commissioned artwork have been put in there, and
That's a process that will continue as we develop the park itself. We are about to bring in the first of the schemes for bicycles that people will be able to use within the existing park facility. But we'll certainly be looking at bike access being a
available within the park under both the bylaws and under the practical side of of how that's going to be achieved. No, we just have to recognise as part of the design that there are no cars on the site. Bikes will be probably the only form of transport other than your legs to get you around the site, except.
for the disabled, and so that's an important step forward. And I think on your final point in regard to local talents, we are continually involved in in looking for local talents across all of the areas of our activity, whether it be on the building side, on the art side, or on the
broader arts administration side, I think it was recognised in the chief executive's policy address a sum of some 150 million to help with the training of local arts administrators to both deal with the needs of West Cowlun, of L.C.S.D. and A.D.C. and so we are looking all the time.
We have done surveys of local capacity and will continue to look at ways that can play to the local talents issue.
誒，公眾參與嗰方面，我就係想聽清楚先。有咩有關公眾參與？
我 probably am reluctant to commit. I think the idea that the public can choose the artworks is something that I'm not prepared to do at this point, because I think Dr Nitfer and his team would have a definite view on that. We'll clearly be communicating as we have all the way through public engagement.
The park was described as the 18th cultural venue. It was the part of the project that received most public comment through the three stages of public engagement. And clearly, we would be we hope that with the event that's on the site over the coming six weeks on the actual site of M Plus.
我會get， I'm sure we will get lots of positive， but I'm sure we'll also get some negative comment， and we'll be able to use that as an interesting opportunity to inform future decisions。我我依家即係嗱喺藝術嘅選擇，我哋絕對相信專家嘅。我誒，只不過點解會特別要提呢個公共？
參與咧，因為咧，誒，其實你哋可以係作為一個參考，起碼係一個參考。因為有時有一啲嘅肖像，可能對於當地嚟講，佢係唔接受，係嘛？你擺咗喺度，或者有突然間好多公眾話做咩？你要擺呢樣嘢喺嗰度，噉你可以呢一方面咧，其實你就可以減少咗啦。你有呢個情
在嘅話，咁可能某一啲肖像係誒，你知道可能係當地人係唔唔唔唔係好接受嘅，咁噉你咪可以誒誒確保咧，喺一啲肖像擺咗喺度，係設計品，係受受歡迎同埋接納。
主席。
嗱誒，而家我睇嘅嗰啲圖咧，我就即係睇到個誒，即係一個大概啫。就我想，我剛才聽係阿Michael講話咧，誒短期內你哋會做個最後拍板嘅。我想清楚一件事。
誒係咪咧噉樣？第二件咧就我想提翻就話，因為成個西九咧係社工瓊。
一個好靚嘅我哋臨海地方，但係我而家睇翻你啲圖咧，我就覺得即係如果你構思裏邊有剛才單鏡，我唔反對嘅。另外就話沿海嘅邊嗰度咧，到底你個綠化係咪一路咁帶到去誒去到最盡尾咧？我又睇唔到喎。即係我見你只係去到某點上。
當你去到Empress嗰度就停咗落嚟㗎，即係我覺得一個咁靚海邊，如果你伴以一啲好靚嘅樹咧，我覺得一個好舒服地方嚟嘅。即係我覺得你要嗰個設計上，你要善用海邊，同埋我哋香港城市人真係好想有啲空間行啊等等，即係各種訴求有咧。咁呢個我亦都想問一路。
去到東邊嗰邊咧，你就因為有建築物，你就冇停咗落嚟。第二個就想問咧，呢個叫做優樹優樹苗圃啊，佔地都幾大。我想問佔幾多地啊？呢個優樹苗圃點樣做㗎？因為我都幾驚政府如果擺啲苗圃樹咧，好似我哋獅山公園噉樣咧，佔地好大㗎。我成日問佢佔大。
地啊！如果你家管理得唔好，直情到時就即係總之好精彩啦噉樣噉就想問點樣佔地咁大先噉啊？另外咧就我當然誒，即係我諗咧，海邊放風箏都個好事，但當我唔堅持，我想提醒下大家，即係有個咁好海邊就唔使行車飛機唔經過嘅，係咪諗諗下呢啲小型嘅嘢咧？
咁即係主題也，即係呢個內容豐富啫。嗱，我主要關心苗圃，關心個綠廊。唔該。O K，誒西九嗰啲個拍搭個苗圃。
誒或者或者可以打一打個苗圃一個check出問題誒個苗圃嘅個目的咧就係話我哋早啲咧種啲樹先咧，將來我哋嗰個誒成個公園起好嗰陣時咧，啲樹苗啊嗰啲種到佢咁大咧，係搬翻落去嗰個公園嗰度，即係唔係嗰個苗圃咧就係依個permanent嘅，即係依個係個。
臨時嘅，咁即係做咗呢幾年之後咧，啲葉啲樹大咗咧，就會搬去擺翻落去嗰個。你幫我寫住喺文字上寫住，我怕到時你揾康文處，佢要你預留一啲畀佢，噉就好精彩㗎。我想講，即係我覺得嗱，我就我同意嘅。你而家喺個種嘅個人當中嘅地方擺啦，但係佢佔地幾大嘅而家，噉。
佢當時將來點咧？咁呢個我覺得你清楚啲寫落先。噉你繼續，好啊。
誒，再冇繼續打。
個綠色廊嗰度咧，其實一路去到東邊嘅，直去嘅。依度我哋冇show到就喺幅圖嗰度，因為成個海濱長廊咧係由西至東嘅，OK，整條嘅，就唔會話去到誒，即係唔會斷咗㗎啦，一路直去嘅。好啊好啊，噉就係誒，我諗啊，主席，我經常問你係而家仲喺雪在傾嘛？自
最後拍板嘅係咪短期內拍板？我哋有冇機會睇？如果你拍板前你改變又點咧？我都想問啊，主席唔該。係咁有冇咩改變咧？拍板前會唔會？We will we will make the decision very soon of the design team and and that will be um something that we would be there would be a very public piece of information.
In terms of the design, and just to go back to your question, part of the master plan that already exists for West Kaloon protects a twenty metre stretch of the waterfront around the whole two two kilometres of the site, so that people will be able to get access to the water.
And be able to make sure they can do all of those things that they would want to do, from the the typhoon shelter end of the site all the way around to Canton Road.
O.K.，主席，我又關心，當你拍板嘅時候咧，如果有條件話咧，即係公公開啊。我驚你理論上就唔會好大變嘅，但我希望就真係，如果有好大變，都話翻畀我哋聽啦，好嘛？唔該。O.K.噉啊，有咩變化就話翻畀誒本局誒本委委員會聽啦，好嘛？
咁跟住落嚟，下一位何秀蘭。
主席，嗱，成份文件咧有一半係講個管理嘅扶例嘅，所以我都係會問嗰個扶例㗎啦。噉就誒喺舊年咧，就誒好快脆就誒將一啲扶例咧，即係本來係康文處嘅咧，就變成係西九管理局自己裏邊嘅規例。噉我。
我哋睇嘅時候咧，就發覺比康文署嗰啲附例仲辣嘅添。例如，即係唔畀放風箏噉，但係咧，我哋都瞭解到有一啲活動，譬如話放模型飛機啊，可能係會影響公眾安全嘅。呢個係好小心，因為我哋誒過去都發發生過一個意外，即係有人畀。
誒模型飛機咧係撞到係重創嘅，咁所以咧就今次文件就表表達咗係會參考外國嘅公共空間嗰啲規管嘅法例嚟同我哋傾咧，呢個我表示歡迎，但係咧。
我亦都擔心嗰個執行，因為咧誒，如果我哋誒就算做咗呢套扶例係以寬鬆為主，正如頭先誒Mr. Lynch講係以寬鬆為主，但係即係我哋誒執行嘅人可能係警隊嘅時候咧，就都好難寬鬆。你知我哋啲警隊而家越嚟越神經好緊張。
即係喐下就即係放噴霧嚇。咁而一個誒執行規管嘅隊伍咧，係有一啲機構文化要慢慢去建立。我畀一個例子，好似我哋立法會嘅保安隊伍噉，我哋對傳媒咧係非常之友善寬鬆。
但係一般過嚟新大樓，因為換咗一個工作環境咧。
都忽然間變咗態度，要要做翻一年先能夠調教翻過嚟，所以呢個機構文化咧係好重要。我想即係問西九管理局，就係佢哋將來係揾乜嘢人做呢個執行規例咧？呢度有提到。
誒授權管理局或其代理人，咁呢啲代理人係乜嘢咧？噉我希望西九咧係可以參考立法會嗰個模式，我哋自己有自己嘅保安，有自己嘅機構文化，真係係對誒示威嘅市民同埋傳媒朋友咧，都係非常之。
寬鬆，但係到某一個程度覺得自己係不能夠執行秩序嘅時候咧，然後就係請即係警隊冇辦法啦，到時都要請警隊去幫手。噉我希望西九管理局咧係可以揾到一個真係能夠落實呢個嘅寬鬆使用公共空間嘅行政方。
方法出嚟，咁或者誒？
西九管理局，即係而家有冇一個誒即時回應咧？同埋誒而家中間係咪仍然以規管工地安全嘅方法去規管呢個臨時公園咧？
It's really important, as I've said before here and in a lot of the public discussion, that the park creates a really special venue for the people of Hong Kong. Clearly, the culture of how we run the park is an important part of the development of both the design, our workforce, the existing facilities manage.
that we have as our responsibility, and as we made out, the first sets of rules were to deal with the transition from LCSD management of part of the site to the fact that it's a very complicated, potentially dangerous site at various times in terms of the building projects that are going on, but
We will be very much involved in the management and the setting up of the those arrangements. We would only envisage the role of the police being involved on the site if there were no extraordinary circumstances. We believe that we will physically set up the park in a way that's going to work. We will manage the.
the park and the facilities in the park in a way that works and that you know under and we have already established through the the hundreds of thousands of people over the course of the last year that have visited the park, including big events like the Poon Choi for twenty six thousand, the Clock and Flap, the Free Space Festival.
That we've been able to do it in a way which I think has caused very little discomfort or unhappiness for the participants, whether they were coming for free or whether they were buying tickets, and we would see that as very much the way forward.
which I hope will make you very happy, bearing in mind your long-standing interest in this issue.
嗱，我我我想補充一句啊，呢個唔係你滿意嘅問題，你哋係提早噉樣係廢除咗個扶例，而有自己制定自己嘅規則去管理個地方咧，其實係。
唔啱嘅，因為你已經係使到而家呢個咧冇法啦去管你哋。我希望下次你就唔可以咁做，因為喺一次會議咧，所有嘅議員都係指責你哋呢個做法嘅。OK，下一位張麗雲。
No, I think we we had a long discussion of it. You know, last time we put in place. Okay, next.
上嚟雲。
唔該啊，主席。
嗱，噉我咧就誒有一建議啦，因為直到而家咧，我睇到咧就係嗰個公園咧都未有一個名稱嘅，咁咧就誒，所以你暫時咧就暫時叫住中央公園。噉我喺呢度咧再一個建議啦，因為既然你呢個地方都叫西九龍文化區啦，咁會唔會考慮直頭？
乾脆將你個公園嘅名稱叫做文化公園咧嚇，咁會唔會更貼切啊？
咁呢個係一個建議。咁另外咧就係誒有關呢一個圖設計，因為呢個圖佢可能係一個暫時或者點樣咧，即係比比較簡單，但係咧就所以我睇唔到太多嘢。噉啊啱啱一個啊幼樹苗圃嗰度咧，就阿陳議員已經亦都提出咗啦，但我。
到係睇到而家咧，你廁所咧就得兩個咗，係咪兩個地點啊？啱唔啱啊？
Well, we have many locations for toilets for individual events, but with two fixed locations.
O K，就啊，月啊，你話即係意思係仲有好多細嗰啲臨時廁所嘅，係咪係咪咁咧？Because there's two big locations, right? You mean that this is two big啊啊啊啊啊啊toilet? There's呃呃呃there's still啊some small one or something? We still have
係，我諗，Mr. Lee，唔好對話，好冇咧。畀佢問完曬之後，我試你講，好冇咧。
sorry, Mr Chairman.
你繼續問啦，張小姐，你問完先，問完未？
誒係係咪係咪就係呢？即係好簡單啫。有幾嚇？因為我見到係個距離好遠啊。係咪中間仲有啲小嘅洗手間呢？
係咪中間仲有少啲細菌，Mr.林？
We will have.
We will have toilet facilities in all all different parts of the park when the park is designed. At the moment, this is that the map you're referring to is the map that guides us through both the building process and the temporary uses of of the of the park. So we still have permanent toilets down on the the waterfront.
front side of the the site, and we we then put in for individual events. We put in temporary toilets for each of those events on the site. You will see next week with the event, there there are toilet facilities in the vicinity of the actual event itself.
O.K.O.K.噉我另外我就誒想再跟住啊問一下咧，就係有關呢個誒附例嘅權力。噉啊附例權力嗰度咧，而家係嗯其實誒民政或者係民政有人睇到啦。噉我想問一問，而家除咗係西九呢一度咧，就想將呢一個。
和海濱呢個啊長廊同埋呢個公園係交畀佢管理，仲有冇其他嘅情況係啊？即係單獨撥出嚟嘅，係畀另一個局去管理啊，或者係咩咧？
冇嚇，睇咧就例如好似海洋公園噉，佢都有自己嘅附例嘅嚇，咁即係佢嗰個範圍就即係由佢自己去管理。係啊係啊，不過我就想咧就係誒要要要，我我我即係可以誒誒想像到啦，就因為佢個同海洋公園嘅情況唔同，海洋公公園好歸一㗎。
嚇，即係包住咗噉樣嘅。咁但係佢呢一個地方咧，就係啊，牽涉到係啊海濱長廊啦。咁咧，因為誒好多附近啲居民咧係朝早過去做晨運嘅，噉就你可能要好早開嚇，或者要好夜。噉你係咪全？
全天候開放式咧噉，因為其他海濱長廊人哋可以放㗎嘛，夜晚可以行下行下，㗎瞓唔著都可以出嚟散步啊嘛。噉你度係咪會噉樣做咧？咁噉就我啱啱咧就聽到啊啊啊何議員話啊啊有位議員話誒呢一個啊係唔畀做呢個放風箏啊噉樣。噉我想知道何解？
同埋係喺誒。
我我文件我揾唔到，噉我知係咪係咪啊？呢個已經定咗一啲嘢咧，咁或者喺文件呢度未有咧，或者我未睇到咧？唔該，邊位答？
阿賴太好啊！咁誒，佢嗰個開放時間咧，其實就誒現時喺嗰個臨時個用途嚟講咧，佢哋都係即係參照翻過往康文處管理嗰個海濱長廊嗰陣時嗰個開放時間嘅。噉就誒，應該都係朝頭早六點去到夜晚十一點噉樣嘅嚇。噉就即係係維持翻嘅。
咁誒將來嚟講就亦都即係誒西九管理局亦都會係要考慮翻，即係用家嗰個意見去定定嗰個開放時間啊。
誒，西金冇補充啦。Add something, you know, clearly at the moment, no, it is only practical for us to go from six in the morning until eleven at night. Um, the issue you've raised will be something we'll be discussing as we, you know, move to the design phase. And I have to say, I'm not entirely sure why we don't let kites fly. Um.
It's probably something that I need to go and do some more research on to be able to ascertain if that's a burning issue for the people of Hong Kong. I may well be able to find a way to resolve that issue.
at least on part of the side，我諗呢個你翻去自己諗啊，因為係你自己制定話唔準放風箏㗎嚇。
Okay, prepare your mind.
好，下一位，誒，梁家傑副主席。
好啊！多謝主席。主席，我誒想問一問咧，就係嗰個誒。
關於嗰個種啲咩樹同埋植物嗰度咧，因為咧就誒之前都有我哋嘅議員關注到咧，因為嗰度係一個即係填海區啦，咁會唔會係有某一啲植物係不適合喺嗰度生長嘅咧？咁噉我就知道你哋而家有一個。
幼樹苗圃喺度咧，咁亦都已經誒種試種咗一啲品種嘅啦。咁可唔可以交代一下，即係而家嗰個進度係點？即係第日我哋喺呢個公園度見到啲咩植物咧？咁呢個一一點啦。第二咧，亦都誒想跟一跟咧，就係關於嗰個誒西九。
管理局咧，就住管理。
誒呢一個誒公園啊！
啊！
即係你根據你個西九管理局、文化區管理局嗰個條例，你係有權制定嗰個有關嘅管理嘅符例嘅。咁嗰度嘅進展個進度又係點咧？噉我想聽埋啫，主席。好啊，請答。
Okay, Mr. Chairman, thank you. On the trees, the whole point of the consortium of landscape designers and park designers that we're using will be very much addressing the fact that it is a reclaimed site, and that their designs will incorporate the capacity to be able to make sure that the trees grow.
and live and and prosper, and the
If you look at the nursery site, it's both to grow trees to get them to an advanced stage, but it's also a research and development facility for a fact that I think that that is a piece of water that's been reclaimed, and from that point of view, it poses some real challenges both in terms of climate, environment and sustainability.
of of what we put on the site and that's clearly one of the priorities in the period leading up to you know the the completion of the the park design and the park construction.
And on your second point，主席，呢第一點我今日講就係，即係Are you happy with the progress？
I mean the research and development, the research and development. Well, the nursery is just being set up, and from that point of view, I think it's we've got a period of time to be able to take advantage of that research and development facility to make sure what we do is going to work.
主席，我想問第二個問題，請請佢答。邊個答第二個問題？唔重複。
On the bylaws issue, we will be, we have indicated we will bring the completed draft of the bylaws back to discuss with the Legco. I think it's clearly something that I may have misunderstood in the first discussions of the importance, and clearly we recognise that we've had ongoing discussions.
with HAB around that issue and we'll make sure that now as soon as we've got that completed, we're doing research project on a number of major international parks in various parts of the world and now we look forward to resolving that issue alongside the time that the park is properly open to the public in the.
Interim, you know, we've had to have a set of rules to guide both our team and potential users. If I could have an indication of what the timetable is like for that bylaw-making process.
Well, I guess what we're looking at is trying to do it as fast as we can, but the they won't come into play for probably you know the first part of the park won't open for at least 18 months.
所以，他們不會在運作。所以，有好多時間 for for the discussion here and in the other appropriate places.
誒，多謝主席。噉啊，我我補充咧，你個巴羅咧，你曾經講嘅係一三一四年咧就要做好嘅，所以你應該喺嚟緊呢個年度，即係而家呢個年度咧，要一定要做好嘅，而唔係話好多時間嘅，呢個要記住啦，好嘛？下一位。
哦，劉慧卿唔喺度。
咁誒有冇其他委員問？如果冇啊，我問。
係，誒誒，我問咗先啦，你第二輪。
我想問啊，跟進啊副主席嘅問題咧，你而家所話研究啲樹咧，即係我哋好擔心嘅，因為嗰笪地方咧係好大風，唔似嗰啲土壤係填海。
即係做乜都死。
即係我唔知點解你哋會揀呢個啦，揀咗就冇計啦。咁好唔好？你哋做咗一個研究之後，未去買之前。
都可以徵詢康文署啊，甚至好多專家，因為我哋康文署好有呢啲豐富嘅經驗。
即係你話翻畀我哋本委員會、本本小組委員會聲啦，你哋會揀選乜嘢樹木，點樣安排嚇？因為我哋好擔心嗰個嗰個維護費用啊，你持續性嘅維護費用咧係好高呢樣嘢。第二咧就係話你而家依個設計咧已經係舊年咧十二月廿八號。
已經開始誒徵攞收收集啦，咁亦都係誒收唔到我哋最近一兩次會議對於嗰個費用個抗傷啦，嗰個關注啦，因為個高，但係我哋咧。
誒，雖然你個設計裏邊內容咧，就冇話將依個誒，我唔知啦，有冇話將依個費用啦、成本費用咧，係擺到好重要嘅位置，擺高咗分。但係我覺得依樣嘢都係我哋要去考慮嘅依樣嘢。誒，又冇新加啲嘢啦，新加咗啲嘢又有一個藉口，又攞多啲錢啦。依啲我哋都。
好擔心，好擔心嘅依樣嘢，咁希望咧就喺你哋。
誒唔知咩時間？你話話畀我聽咩時間？你會畀做到大概呢個費用係估算到係係幾多畀我哋？
咁如果太多嘅仇咧，我哋真係要考慮下，再係噉樣去設計嘅時候咧，無休止咁去即係攞錢咧，我哋覺得咧呢樣嘢咧係一個非常恐怖嘅情況，好嘛？你哋樹木嗰度第一問題，樹木嗰度可唔可以答覆？一定要翻嚟畀我哋做好一個長。
詳細研究先，OK。
I think in terms of the park, it's a much more.
controlled part of the project than the sixteen seventeen other buildings on the site. So from our point of view, as soon as we've resolved the design, we will be able to do that. We have a increasingly clear view of that, but you need the design. There are a range of issues that impact on the park.
As you know, Mr. Chairman, there's a Western Harbour Tunnel. There's the Airport Express. There are a range of other complications that mean that we have to address some infrastructure issues. The issue of the basement under the the other end of the building clearly create issues for us, and we're in discussions with the government.
on those issues at the moment, and that will come back as part of the overall costing.
啲樹木嗰度冇問題係咪？我見到啊，李生都合頭，即係你會同康文處或者香港嘅外地嘅專家研究下呢度種啲咩適合嘅植物。主席係我哋好好關心嗰啲樹嘅，當然啦。係頭先你講得好啱，嗰度係好大風，我哋要誒同康文處亦都有啲專家睇嘅嚇。
Okay.
咁咧就我冇提問啦嚇。第二輪啊，要問嘅可以繼續舉手。第二輪，蔣麗雲。
好啊，唔該，主席，我淨係想問一個問題咧，就係喺嗰個啊文件佢第八、第九段咧，咁咧就係佢而家管理局咧就啊有一啲地方咧係嗯即係定啊有一個叫啊租用有臨時有一個活動區嘅一啲甄選準則㗎，噉我。
想知道咧就嗯過去租出誒多唔多咧噉，或者係啊你哋嘅收費又點樣咧咁？咁咧就同埋啊直到目前為止，你哋個收入又有幾多咧？
得得得，That that's the next item, isn't it, Mr. Chairman?
哦，OK，下一個先至答你啦，仲有冇其他問題？哦，OK。
如果冇咧，我哋就完咗呢個議程嚇。
冇，下一個咧就係。
關於依個。
西九文化區嘅計劃建築工程嘅展開前，西九文化區嘅用地管理同埋使用情況，啊！請舉手。
噉啊，或者我就當啊，上嚟話頭先嘅問題係第一條問題啦。我我啱啱個問問題你有冇聽到咧？有聽到我唔使再問一次啦。咁慳翻啲時間，你直接答我啦。唔該。好。
啊！
I understand, Dr. Chan. Your question relates to the selection criteria that we use for allowing events on the site. And I guess in summary, we look at the key criteria outlined under paragraph 8 of the paper: nature and impact of the event.
site availability and feasibility and the credibility and track record of the organisers. And we've applied that to the over 50 events I think that we've conducted over the course of the last year. I think quite successfully, and we've been able to utilise a good mix of what are
not-for-profit activities related to arts and cultural activity, as well as some commercial activities that help contribute to being able to do the the free activities that we've been able to undertake on the site.
So is there any income? Yes, I think we we stated in that over the course of the last year we've taken about four million dollars for projects that we've conducted on the site, and all of that money has then been put in.
到The free activities that have taken place, things like the Free Space Festival and the Chinese Orchestra Festival and the M Plus Inflation Event, which will open this week.
所以我們用任何收入從使用公園來貢獻到能夠擺出一連串的免費活動在場地，來確保我們吸引觀眾，但我們也建立對公園最終將會是什麼的意識。
噉你點樣可以分到咧？有啲可以係免費畀佢哋用嘅場地，有啲咧就要收錢咧。
係加緊。
I guess we take somewhat of a Robin Hood approach. The we no, I use the example of the wedding event, which has had already some discussion in this chamber, where we charge the people putting the wedding. It was not on a public part of the the actual site. We charge them a
substantial amount of money to be able to then use that money to contribute to the free activities that take place. We look at the we look at the business proposal from any of the people. If it's a community organisation, if it's a charitable organisation, then we or an arts and cultural organisation or one of our of
events we are very lenient in terms of of how we do that. If it's a film event, we are very
actively encouraging using those events, but if it is a commercial event, we think that the people should make an appropriate contribution so that we can pay for some of the the other events that we want to do.
So who makes the decision? My executive team under my leadership make the decisions on who gets in there and and if it exceeds a certain amount of money, that gets referred up to either the development committee or the board. I suggest you should make it. Yeah, I suggest you.
全明，clearly outline，so then all your staff can follow. Thank you.
算高啦。
誒，多謝主席。啊，頭先咧就。
提過一個嘅婚禮。
咁咧喺十一月中咧就誒有傳媒報道咧就有一個富豪嘅婚宴咧就喺西九文化區咧就舉行，噉我其實都都關心嘅，咁所以我都寫一封信咧係畀誒呢個管理局嘅主席，亦都係我哋嘅政務司司長林鄭月娥，係十一月二十三號嘅信，到今日佢都未。
復我。
噉我都好想知道咧，透過呢個會議搞清楚呢一件事，到底係點樣申請，向邊一個申請啊？邊個去負責審批？乜嘢嘅條件同埋咧？呢一個婚宴嘅收支嘅情況係點樣？我希望咧就誒，我哋嘅關。
關注咧，係在於會唔會西九文化區嘅某個部分？
嘅屬於公眾嘅空間啊，同埋我哋嘅屬於公眾嘅一個資源咧，係被私有化，係畀人咧係攞嚟做自己嘅啊富豪嘅派對，或者咧係一啲嘅活動。因為如果就咁睇咧，照計嚟講咧，我都想問啊，如果呢個此例一
開係咪即係話西九文化管理局因為要用頭先剛才所講嘅Robinhood？
嘅做法即係劫富濟貧啦，我理解嚇劫富濟貧嘅做法就係話你而家可以啦，向全世界公開話咧，只要嚟我哋嗰度，只要你有錢，我就會幫你安排咧婚宴啊。而講緊嘅數目咧係可以同你咧係逐次逐次去傾啊。我理解咧西九傳信同。
埋呢一個嘅啊推廣嘅行政總監咧，陳家耀先生喺回應傳媒訪問嘅時候咧，係好好驕傲地講咧，我哋今次賺咗好多錢嘅。咁可唔可以都講埋啦？嗰個次你賺咗幾多錢，主席？O.K.想抖抖。
I think I've already said in regard to the wedding. Please do not misunderstand me in regard to that event. The Robin Hood comment was meant to be a reflection of the fact that that is the the one event that we've done like that that has achieved a substantial amount of money we received in excess of.
1 million Hong Kong dollars, but there was much more money spent on the event in the creation of that event. We looked at that event alongside the criteria. You will see in Annex Two of the paper, the document that is publicly available for use on the site. What the
application procedure is what the eligibility is, and what the reasons that we outline. They then have to provide that to us. That is considered by my executive team on a regular basis. It is consistent with the permitted uses under the S.T.T. and from our
Our point of view, and what we're looking at is a balanced mix of activities, the ability to generate income to cover the operating expenses, which were not given under the endowment, and I guess to create some sense of what the future of the site is going to be—that there will be a mix of cultural.
And commercial activities. In regard to the wedding event, they had brought in major entertainment players from Canada, and they needed to create a very specific public space. It did not obstruct the normal use of the site by the public. And if I go back to my previous experience of running venues.
在London and in Australia, at the Sydney Opera House, we used to make a lot of money to contribute to the artistic program from running weddings and similar activities. And so I don't think we have any in principle objection as long as there is a benefit to the broader community or that we can.
主席啊，佢佢嗰度咧係講緊個人申請咧，一般咧係不獲考慮嘅。咁所以嗰個嘅婚禮到底係一個乜嘢類型性質嘅申請？可唔可以講清楚？可以講清楚。嗰次賺咗一百萬嘅婚禮咧，係一個集體嗰個婚禮活動啦，亦或係。
It was not a private application. It was done by a major. I think the Hong Kong economy gained some ten million US dollars from this wedding. From our point of view, we only got one million. I wish I'd probably ask for more, but it was done by a major consortium of production companies in Hong Kong who went through the.
the relevant approval process and provided us with that information, and we made the decision to go ahead on that basis. So the application was submitted by Suncorium, but eventually it turned out to be a wedding for a Russian Chinese couple, right? Correct. Correct.
You think there's anything wrong with that idea? What the idea of a Russian marrying a Chinese couple? Or no, I mean the the fact that you're holding a wedding. Well, I wasn't holding the wedding. It was in a non-public part of the space, and we rented it out. And my simple view is that the the one million dollars that we received from.
From running the wedding was then invested into the Free Space Festival, where we brought twenty thousand people there over the weekend in December, and we were able to use that one million dollars to contribute to the artistic program for the Free Space Festival. Unless there are in principle objections, I.
I don't see any problem with the idea of being able to do appropriate commercial activity there to ensure that we're able to do big events for the public. In the same way, we have charged a number of organisations that are commercial organisations that are making money, different levels of.
of charge to make sure that those events take place on the site, but know that they know they're not at a disadvantage。我我諗時間都夠啦，你都説服唔到我哋，因為你之前嘅例即係規則就話唔準租畀私人嘅活動，但係而家你見到見錢眼開，又見到人哋畀一百萬，你又租畀人哋去。
噉我諗你翻去再諗清楚，睇下點樣去搞清楚依件事，係咪話你以後都會誒好彈性處理？只要有錢你就有有得傾㗎啦，噉樣啊？咁依依樣你你自己再諗一諗，再答翻我哋啦，好嘛？下一位何秀娜，誒唔該主席，誒我相信西九管理局咧。
都要吸取上一趟嗰個誒經驗，即係好好地去誒釐清自己一啲租用場地嘅規管。雖然我哋見到咧，就誒譬如香港藝術中心，即係灣仔嗰邊咧，佢都有誒透過租用場地，甚至係租畀一啲餐廳，去得到一啲經常性嘅收入。但係呢啲。
規則咧，我相信係要寫得好清楚，亦都係要同公眾諮詢，咁定到一個準則，唔好畀人哋覺得咧就用咗公堂同埋公眾嘅地方去畀私人去做自己嗰個慶祝活動，呢個係非常之重要嘅。希望西九管理局明白。咁主席我就要問第四段嘅，我我見到。
佢咧就話試行一個租用單車自動系統，啊，我就好開心見到呢個。但係咧，我一個意見一個問題，意見咧就係請誒西九就要不要忘記兒童喺呢個自動誒租用單車系統嗰度咧，就唔好淨係得。
啲好高嘅單車，因為西九係一個一家大細去嘅地方，就一定要有一啲細架啲，畀啲細路哥咧都可以同誒爸爸媽媽大家一齊喺西九嗰度誒踩單車周圍行。咁希望誒西九管理局記得。第二咧就好不幸咧，香港誒雖然係一個好安全嘅城市。
但係，我哋亦都係一個渠蓋都有人叫佢買嘅城市。咁誒，呢啲誒有價值嘅東西咧，誒係會誒被偷取，係會唔見嘅。咁所以呢個自動單車系統咧，我哋喺第度見到咧就好方便嘅，入一個誒硬幣或者入錢入去咧就可以。
掹咗出嚟，誒試到啱噉啊，然後攞走就去第二點嗰度咧，去到目的地啦，就誒大家好守規矩擺翻入去。咁但係我哋香港咧，真係渠蓋都有人叫噉啊！噉我哋點樣防止呢啲單車誒踩出西九去到其他地方咧？咁可唔可以同我哋介紹一下呢個試行？
系統係點嘅咧？
O.K.講講佢係噉。We will take either your credit card or your Octopus card or your Hong Kong identity card, and we will make sure that you comply with the laws and that you can't steal the bikes.
即係唔收錢嘅，就一定要拍卡。O K，即係呢呢個呢個另一方面，大家又要即係諗翻自己嗰啲私隱啦。咁誒誒請即係西九管理局誒喺呢個試行租用單車系統有多啲細節嘅時候咧，都誒請同我哋誒交代翻啊。唔該，主席。O K，有冇回應？
如果冇，OK。
噉啊，下一位劉慧卿委係誒，多謝主席。主席唔好意思嚇，頭先嗰度誒，我我唔喺度啊，因為好多人想問聽日四川嗰個撥款啦嚇誒。主席啊誒，我就同意頭先你同埋同事講咧，就係話佢哋租用嗰啲場地咧，佢要講講翻清楚嗰個準則啦。頭先啊啊啊連啊。
立志先生，阿連立志先生講又話有啲係私人嘅，有啲係公共嘅，噉我都唔係好清楚。即係你唔好畀人哋有個印象，即係你哋裏邊係好混亂啊，或者有啲即係做有啲唔應該做嘅嘢啦。噉我希望你呢度可唔可以解釋清楚啲？即係其實如果你做啲嘢去揾到啲錢去做啲更大嘅嘢咧，可能未必係有問。
係嘅，但係係你點樣搞咯？同埋個準則係咪大家都知道？咁呢度咧，我相信越清楚係好。如果大家都知道係啱嘅，咁咪去做咯。如果係唔好嘅、唔恰當嘅咧，就唔好做。噉就誒，另外咧就係嗰個呢度提到嗰個通達性咧，主席即係成個場地咧，我哋都係一路都係好關。
心嘅真係你好好嘅嘢喺裏邊都冇用嘅。如果啲人唔識去，去唔到噉，所以咧，我希望你哋做嘅時候都諗多啲，有冇啲係即係有啲嗰啲電梯啦，即係嗰啲自動行人嗰啲，即係唔使行得咁辛苦啊。或者有冇車去車啲人啦，嗰啲誒即係唔會污染嗰啲車，同埋好多牌啊。
周圍擺曬啲牌，令到啲人可以睇到，唔會喺度行冤枉路。我覺得呢啲設計都係非常之即係喺一個另一個好友善、好舒服嘅環境，令到人喺好容易知道自己想去邊度就去到。噉我請你哋答一答啊，唔該。Okay。
西九，Mr.林。
Well, you know, Ms. Lau, that accessibility is one of our key concerns. But clearly, we're not in a position through temporary use to do anything other than be able to transport people to the site, make sure they have a safe and pleasant experience. But as part of the design of the park.
The whole issue of accessibility is one of the key criteria for the park designers, and we'll be continually looking at at that issue. In regard to your first point, what we were saying is that it wasn't public issue. Is that it wasn't on the waterfront space that the public is kept.
open for the public either through the preparation or on the actual event itself. It was done for one night in regard to the the wedding event, and then the public was able to access the know the normal parts of the site that they have access to the next day.
I don't understand, Chairman. So there is a public area and a private area, in which certain individuals can get access with money. Please explain clearly. No, no, no. When I'm talking about the pub, there was a public part. There are parts of the site that can be used for events, but there have no interest to the.
The area around the airport express exhaust or the area around the western tunnel exhaust clearly are not sort of public spaces. But the space that we used for the event that Dr Chan's already questioned us about.
was not inhibiting public use to the waterfront facilities. Chairman, I don't think that's the point. The point is whether there are rules which are equal and fair.
And I don't care whether it's near the waterfront or not. But if that area is open to any member of the public, then it should be make accessible. I I don't understand your your your explanation, Chairman. This is not fair. That's why members have asked you to go back and to revise the rules, whether it's for
Using the area near the waterfront or in other locations, it should be fair and should be open. And now, I don't think you have answered my question. I'm sorry, Mr. Lynch. I can't let parts of the site that might be dangerous or might know in terms of children or
public access. We have the the site has been controlled in that sense for much longer than we have had any involvement with it. Now there are fences. There are parts of the site that are fenced off. Now there were commercial arrangements on the site for many years in terms of, no access points that you could get to. All
我係講，係就
我哋唔會限制公眾使用嘅。
即係公平性，即係而家你話你本應制定嘅例話唔畀私人用嘅，誒你畀我講埋先嘛？佢唔畀私人用嘅，但係而家你因為話人哋可以畀到錢一百萬搞依個活動，噉你覺得有錢賺你就用啦。咁會唔會啊？我想用我，但我畀得十萬啫，你畀唔畀？
畀我用啦！你又唔畀我用咯喎？噉你究竟個批質喺邊度咧？你可唔可以講清楚？
Well, that's not, Mr. Chairman. That's not true. I didn't say that. What I said was that we do not allow individual applications to avoid the idea of it becoming an interview. You know, they they have to be submitted in the form in accord with Annex Two of the paper, which I think is.
Quite straightforward. If members don't feel it straightforward enough, then no, we can provide further information. But it's quite extensive in terms of the applications and what we have said. Applications from individuals will generally not be considered, and no, from that point of view, that's the the.
issue in terms of that, we have not said that it would not be used for private use. My earlier comments apply that if we can use it publicly or use it privately to contribute to being able to run events like the Bamboo Theatre Project, the Free Space Festivals, and the other activities.
then we see that as an appropriate mix of activities, and if we can't use it for private use, then we won't be able to do the free activities on the side.
我明白啦，即係話你你自己一個人去申請就唔得嘅，或者你經過一間公司一個團體去申請咧，都係搞私人嘢咧又得嘅噉樣。唔係主席，其實佢咧就話搞嗰啲嘢就揾到啲錢，可以去做其他大啲嘅嘢。咁呢個未必係一定係唔啱嘅。噉佢揾搞嗰啲私人嗰啲嘢啦嚇，去揾錢嗰啲嘢咧都應。
應該係開放畀公眾嘅，邊個有錢就去用佢嗰個地方，就畀啲多啲錢，佢賺到啲錢咧就搞畀其他人。噉你呢啲要攞嚟同大家講咯，就即係話其實你有錢你去搞嗰啲都係有啲規限嘅，唔係個人嘅。咁呢個都係開放嘅，邊個想去搞噉你畀多啲錢啊？我哋賺到一百萬、四百萬。
我哋就可以搞多啲嘢。噉你畀個規矩，大家知清楚咯。O K，噉我諗呢個規係啊，阿黎太或者我補充一點咧，即係因為我據我瞭解咧，其實就即係佢哋啊，其中一個考慮咧，就係去辦呢一啲誒嘅節目嘅機構咧，係咪有個足夠嘅過往嘅經驗啊、能力啊？
去即係舉辦呢一啲噉嘅節目咧，咁咁所以即係從嗰個考慮咧，就所以一般即係如果係個人噉，佢哋就唔會考慮咁噉，或者即係誒，我哋都聽取議員嗰個意見，就係話點樣可以將嗰個考慮啊個誒準則係可以寫得清楚啲，噉啊畀大家都知道噉樣嚇，或者我我哋請管理局翻去考慮下啦。
O.K.誒誒，副主席梁二，多謝主席。
其實咧，我諗啊，Mr. Lincher都應該明白咧。自從即係啊上次喺誒上一屆議會誒臨近尾聲嘅時候咧，即係引起好大嘅迴響咧，就係你突然間刊憲就話將呢一個公眾遊樂場地附例咧係停。
應用於呢一個誒西九管理局所管理嘅嗰啲場地咧，而又代之以一套咧係冇誒呢一個法律效力嘅一啲你自行制定嘅規則。
我相信你應該其實明白嗰個關注咧，個關注咧就係因為你管理嗰個場地係誒公共嘅資源嚟㗎嘛。
咁如果你係冇一套客觀準誠嘅規則咧？
噉就好容易畀人覺得係唔係我識得Mr.Lynch就容易啲咧？咁即係呢個咧就係我諗個關注點咧。咁如果你用呢個角度嚟睇一睇，你而家誒畀我哋嘅附件二咧，其實裏邊有好多。
嘅寫法咧，都可以有好不一。
樣嘅解釋㗎。
即係譬如你你話嗰個可以租用嗰個臨時即係臨時用途啦，嗰啲誒團體係乜嘢咧？噉你就話誒根據社團條例註冊嘅機構啊、公司條例成立機構啊等等。
咁但係呢一個表咧。
表列咧就唔應該係誒一個。
完即係完全不能夠再增加嘅表嚟㗎嘛！
That it is not exhaustive.
咁如果唔係，
誒已經盡列㗎啦。噉你究竟仲有啲咩人可以去申請咧？咁因為你頭先，我啲同事都質疑啦，即係你喺呢個申請資格最後嗰一點咧，你就話個人申請一般不獲考慮。噉係咪如果我透過一間製作公司申請？
我就喺嗰度做一個。
個人show都冇問題咁嗱，呢啲咧就係我諗你要明白，即係我哋嘅關注，而我哋都係殷切期望咧。譬如頭先講嘅嗰個扶例可以盡早去制定啦。喺制定嘅時候，應該咧係從一個。
客觀準誠，大家睇落去覺得公道公平，亦都係有一啲客觀嘅準則嚟到去誒。
監察住你行事咁嚟到去作為一個原則啦啊噉，所以我我想我首先第一就問下阿Mr. Lin，你明唔明白我哋嘅關注咧？即係當我頭先噉樣試圖再解釋一次畀你聽。第二咧，我想問下就係你喺啊？
誒明白咗呢個需要之後咧，你會點樣係盡快回應我哋呢個委員會委員嘅關注同埋對你嘅期許咧？
I certainly understand the concerns of members about the use of public space. It's always one of the much debated issue within my management team about what should be there. But I guess overall, if you look at the range of activities that have taken place on the site over the time that we've been doing.
I think there is only one wedding, and from that point of view, I think it has taken up a disproportionate time of the concern. Clearly, we will be very much guided by the concerns. Clearly, the public events have been much more important, especially the free public events. In
terms of what what has taken place on the site, and from our point of view, we will be very judicious in making the decisions going forward.
啊，主席最後一句咧，誒。
Whether you have promulgated.
and are practising a set of rules that have objectivity and have objective certainty, is.
always tested.
by non-compliance rather than compliance. Yes, I I hope you understand this. I defer to your legal expertise on that issue.主席，我唔係想對話，不過即係我，I I really urge upon the authority to take on board。
The concerns of this joint committee, and to come up with a set of objectively certain rules asap。多少字啫？
多謝。
O.K.
跟住落嚟就係偉全。
誒，多謝主席。就誒，當然利用呢個西九啲場地作為一啲臨時嘅活動咧，即係使到多啲人公眾咧參與咧，就呢個係一個好事嚟嘅。有知即係我哋係成個西九都希望咧，就係誒，即係多啲公眾公眾人士可以享。
講用參與同埋咧，即係亦都利用呢個即係呢個發展，令到嗰啲誒即係藝術即係參與啊。尤其是本地咧，可以多啲發揮。噉我唔知即係誒，因為呢個臨時咧，我唔知道即係管理局會唔會考慮咧。尤其是而家我哋越嚟越多一啲誒，關於喺個設計。
係包括即係即係戲曲中心啊，或者而家Amper啊等等。咁其實喺嗰啲設計嚟講咧，可唔可以考慮一啲展示下即係臨時嘅展示一啲，等公眾知道即係我哋使咁多錢，其實即係做咗揀咗嗰啲嘢係點樣嘅。咁等佢盡早即係認識嚇。
即係呢方面咧，其實係我哋做緊嘢，同埋一啲進展啊。即係利用，即係因為你其實呢個係一個臨時嘅，但係你將來都即係大家都期待誒呢個西九咧發展之後會點咧噉樣？咁唔知會唔會咁做咧？啊，唔該，主席。主席，多謝。
Well, thank you for the suggestion. But you will be aware, I think, that one hundred zero people came to see the exhibition on the zhu in the bamboo theatre precinct during the period around Chinese New Year, and clearly we see it as very important as part of that public engagement that it.
making sure that people know what's coming, and we deliberately set the exhibition alongside the bamboo theatre project because next year the bamboo theatre project will move to the park part of the site where the wedding was.
And then we will hopefully have created the sense of expectation because we will be building on the on the Canton Road site. So take that on board with the future facilities. We'll be making sure that people understand what's coming. It's a very important part of our new website and a range of
議員，我認為這會是一個非常好的建議，特別是如果EMAS會包括建築作為視覺藝術之一的話，那麼這將是一個很好的方式來推廣。
I I would most appreciate you know the management had done so.
Thank you, Chen. Architecture is actually one of the areas that the museum will be covering. Okay.
下一位咧就誒，我哋第一輪講完啦，第二輪咧就有得陳家洛噉，陳家洛繼續提問。我冇嘢講。有冇提問？仲大家有冇提問？係係啊，阿十二。
誒，即是即係今日我聽聽咁耐啲議員講同埋答咧，有時似乎好似對Mr Ling有少少唔係好公平噉。即係但係個問題咧，唔係個個問題唔係喺我議員嗰度，個問題喺西九呢個管理局嗰度，因為西九管理局好似似乎。
乎咧，就係畀唔到我哋有一個訊息，佢即係佢佢佢個目標係乜嘢，目的係乜嘢，佢計劃係點做？雖然我哋睇咗咁多文件，但係當佢答嘅文件，譬如而家頭先好似話係誒婚禮嗰個情況噉啊，誒有好多議員又問啦，即係係咪即係個人？
得啊噉，但係如果即係你有一個準則喺度，冇冇唔理係誒一個富商好，或者係望國順水好，好似個個都有權咁去用，唔應該有依度咧，因為富商佢就唔可以申請用，誒阿順嫂可以申，即係唔係噉嘅意。頭先啊，阿梁議員都。
講得好清楚，每一樣嘢，你個你你又好清晰地，你啲條例係點去擺出嚟咧？西九管理局應該咧就要話曬畀人聽，所以冚唪唥明明確確係陽光化曬佢哋嗰個政策喺度。佢哋有政策要賺錢嘅，又要買而好，又要買而不吃草，就好難嘅。咁但係佢。
西九管理嗰個項目有冇一啲信息出到嚟畀我哋睇到？每一個市民都睇到，佢點去用依個？邊個想用可以申請？Disneyland咧最近都有一個私人嘅派party派party畀一個明星啦。點解西九唔可以用咧？噉啊就雖然誒Disneyland都係。
誒政府同埋Disney一齊去拼嘅，咁但係咧，佢有個噉嘅，如果有個噉嘅需求去用，佢咪講曬出嚟喺佢嘅條，喺佢哋嗰嗰啲誒。
小冊子好，佢哋嗰啲bylaws冇，冚唪唥講曬出嚟。但係而家目前咧，我哋睇唔到佢有依樣嘢，所以可唔可以Mr.Lynch咧，即係翻去依個同依個管理局或者要管管理局誒主席嚟解釋下畀我哋依個委員會依個去聽？就係唔係即係而家嘅Mr.Lynch答嘅問題咧，佢只係係。
董事局嘅政策，而係佢又佢唔超越咗嗰度，所以主席，我諗或者喺呢度咧，係咪有冇需要叫董事局成員嚟去解釋下呢啲呢啲情況？主席，OK，誒，首先Mr.林處先。
I take on board your points, Mr. Sheikh, but I guess the reason that the chairman employs me to run WKCDA is to manage these activities, and clearly I think she's got plenty of other things that she needs to be doing at the moment alongside that. I think from our point of view, we've listened to.
The members, and we'll try and see if there is any points that aren't clear in terms of Annex II, and if there's any more information that we can provide to make it easier for people to understand the criteria and what's happened. The only thing I would say in our defence, we have.
looked at each one of these proposals very carefully, and I think overall we are quite happy with the way that most of those events have taken place. And clearly, we now have a much better understanding of the sorts of events we have given priority to our own events and to arts and culture-related events.
Over all sorts of other activities, we have also the majority of the activities have not been income-producing to us. They've really been geared towards community or cultural use of the site.
問的哥有冇回應？
嗯。
誒我我我或者都可以誒誒睇一提咧，喺文件第九段嗰度咧，就都有誒講咧，就係其實喺考慮呢一啲誒誒租用嘅申請嗰陣時候咧，嗰個主要嗰個誒優先次序咧，係會畀一啲文化藝術嘅節目嘅。咁而誒誒商業性嘅活動咧，其實亦都會係考慮嘅。咁
咁如果係商業性嘅活動咧，就會按市場價格去收取。咁所以就即係其實都係一個公開，即係誒管理局亦都有公開向大家去誒講解，即係誒其實誒除咗管理局自己嘅活動之外咧，其他嘅商業活動都會係誒容許，不過咧就會收市場嘅費用。
誒，仲有冇其他人有提問？
好，第二輪啊，石。
主席頭先即係我聽到Mr. Lynch講咧，即係個人佢就唔即係或者我聽錯咗，個人佢就唔會接受。但係佢話依個嗰個即係嗰個講翻個wedding咧係一個一個好大嘅誒公司去去做嘅。但係我依樣嘢我又我又覺得好唔應該喎。如果個人同我係一間公
公司有咩分別咧？如果你個政策係好清晰地講出嚟，無論係個人好、富商好、窮人好、有錢佬好，都可以申請去有噉嘅資格去，咪申請。但係咧，依因為我哋攞咗依食幾日公挺出嚟，同埋依二百一十億出嚟咧，係一個公眾嘅誒誒，所以可以用嘅公眾咧，無論佢係。
係有錢好冇錢好咧，我係都應該咧係要同時同一一一一一個呢，即係公眾公眾性嘅角度去睇，係可以申請可以用。但係呢頭先佢講，佢明確定佢講出嚟，但係冇明確，佢呢明確話你個人唔可以申請，點可以個人唔可以申請？我想叫佢解釋下。
你唔要再解釋啦。我諗你講咗好多次。I I think the only point about credible organisations is we are concerned about their ability to deliver the event, the ability to manage the safety and and other issues, food safety, people safety. That's the reason that we we judge.
whether the event organiser is a credible organisation with an appropriate track record and can make sure that they're in a position to do that. But I take your point.
我諗咁啦，係阿Bonny嚇。
我想補充，主席。嗯，我想議員睇下咧第二段呢張paper第二段嘅F啊，因為管理局咧係將來唔係淨係管理而家就係空地一塊，將來係會有建築物㗎嘛。咁同埋管理局嘅我哋嗰個mandate係將。
將來要收支平衡嘅咁點收支平衡咧，就有收入有支出啊嘛。咁將將來個收入都係由商業活動嗰度咧攞到收入㗎嘛。咁所以第誒F嗰段就係話，我哋而家空地一塊，我哋都係試下點樣樣試下點樣樣咧，日攞到。
到啲從商業活動攞到啲收入咧，咁嚟幫到我哋嘅支出。我諗，你我諗，西九管理局都聽聽議員講啦，私人都可能大把水嘅，唔係個個好似我噉啊嘛，係咪？所以我覺得咧，你應該問佢有冇能力係啱嘅。佢如果係私人嚟申請，你咪問佢佢會委託咩公司幫佢做，係嘛？你或者佢。
佢用咩方法去做？噉你都要考慮下先啦，唔可以即刻閂咗道門，私人就唔畀，係嘛？有錢就畀噉樣，一養起咗百萬支票，噉你就即刻誒口水都流曬唔得嘅依樣嘢。噉我諗你依樣嘢咧，翻去再研究下，睇下點做啦。反誒，仲有冇同事提問？如果冇，我就我嘅意見咧。
就同阿石議員第一個問題咧就好相同。我而家真係發覺咧，點解會出現咁多問題咧？
就係話咧，民政局啊，你委任嗰班西九管理局嗰班嗰班咩董事局嗰班人咧，管理局嗰班人咧，全部都係社會賢達，但係業餘。
去。
睇住西九管理局行政嗰方面，咁咧就出問題㗎啦！依樣嘢嚇，個個都社會言達，啊公務繁忙，你應該再諗下，將來你再諗下，係唔係要過度去好似管理港鐵噉樣，管理一啲啊事建局噉樣啦？係最低限度都要。
要有一啲人全職噉樣咧去做呢個董事咧，去管理呢個西九管理局咧。如果唔係咧，純粹你好似其他嗰啲啊青啊咩暑期青少年委委員會噉樣去管理咧，就實係多問題出現嘅。你而家根本就管唔到，有有委員就反映喺呢度。
反應話我都唔知佢點樣啊！佢又唔理我，我又唔理佢。你依邊咧就自己一個人做，做完出嚟咧，翻到嚟依度又畀人捉，咁又何苦咧？根本你成個結構上咧，你係出現咗一啲問題。你唔能夠揾一啲業餘嘅人士管咗咁大棚嘅土地同埋嘅設施嘅，你。
你應該係諗一諗，係咪要揾一啲專業嘅全職嘅人士去坐依個管理委員會，坐依個董事局啦，好嗎？依個係我個人意見。
OK。
O.K.如果冇咩有冇咩補充？如果冇咩補充，我哋結束今日嘅會議。喺結束之前咧，我都係。
O.K.
Is.
誒。
啊。
Hello, hello. I think that's what my team's there to do. I think the idea that we are appointed to run the various parts of this project, and clearly, you know, we work well with our board in terms of those responsibilities, and we've cleared these. You know, clearly we escalate those issues up.
到the board level. I don't I don't know that it's actually going to be helped by full-time board members. I I wonder how that actually would work in the good interests of, know the organisation.
噉啊，肯定有幫助啦！即係全時間就好過啲屈不消啦，係嘛？噉係嗱，衞興宇。
Rubber stamp啊，主席你唔係主席啊，我我同意你講，即係我希望咧，即係亦都未必係要全職咯。講你即係全職坐曬嗰度又唔知攞幾多十萬一個月就唔得掂嘅。但係你要揾啲人咧，一係有即係有知識啦，係有公信力。
同埋比較獨立，肯出嚟講説話，亦都講公道嘅説話嘅。
咁希望咧，就係你揾啲嗰啲人，有咩事嘅時候，佢會甚至代表你個管理局出嚟講嘢，而咧人哋係信任嘅，人哋覺得佢係有能力、係公道嘅。咁呢啲我希望你哋揾啦。如果你揾埋曬啲人喺幫唔到你，或者幫倒忙嘅，你自己又揾石頭揼自己嘅腳，即係你哋。
自己去考慮啦，即係但係大家覺得呢件事係要做得好，咁同埋咧，其實咧，我琴日都同兩位嚟見我嗰兩位人士講，我話嗰啲團體咧、啲藝團咧就好大意見，因為而家佢哋未接觸佢哋啊嘛，除咗講個戲曲中心，即係你個管理啊嗰啲，佢哋要參與嘅，即係你有啲持份者，你。
都畀咗佢嘅印象，佢覺得你將佢摒之於門外，咁呢個亦都唔掂。所以咧嗱，佢第日嚟咧，主席，我希望下次嚟佢會話畀我哋聽，佢同嗰啲主要持份者係有份傾傾過，大家吸納咗個意見。噉你第日管理咪暢順啲咯，同埋咧係交出嚟嗰啲數嚇，你啊主。
主席，你都講過幾次又話七月啊嘛，即係你點樣超支法，你要寫曬列出嚟，好詳細講點解係超支，有邊啲係因為通脹，有邊啲係因為你增加咗新嘅設施，係當時計係冇嘅，你即係詳細去交代啦。我希望即係其實呢個計劃，我哋係想去成功嘅，但係成功。
得嚟咧，你係得到社會嘅支持，而唔係喺啲噏聲當中喺度搏命做咯。我諗發表都夠啦嚇，係嘛？你舉手，第二個又舉手，咁一路舉落去，係嘛？第三輪啦，係嘛？都話畀佢聽啊嘛，佢要去處理㗎嘛。噉啊，當第三輪啦，啊，你講完有冇回應啊？啊，如果冇回應啊，下一位議員再發表意見。OK。
好咗啦，主席，我哋個會預咗開到十二點噉啊。當然即係早散就大家可以做多其他嘢啦，但係大家亦都預咗呢個時間。主席啊，嗰個誒董事局嗰度咧，即係我有呢個睇法。我哋誒當然希望一啲好有承擔嘅人用好多時間落去，即係亦都去誒同。
誒行政人員西九管理局嘅行政人員，大家一齊做事。噉我哋唔希望董事局係西九行政人員嘅橡皮圖章，但係我哋亦都唔希望董事局被委任嘅成員係政府嘅橡皮圖章。咁不過好誒兩難咧，就係香港而家。
對文化政策有認知嘅人咧，其實真係唔多，我哋底子唔夠厚，咁所以咧誒，我亦都喺呢度係請西九管理局，我哋喺國際嗰度請翻嚟嘅專才，亦都要盡快去明白我哋香港嗰個文化社會氣候，誒有一啲公眾。
嘅監察，我請大家接受。縱使我哋係誒用一好多時間去講一啲細節，例如呢個婚禮噉樣樣，呢個亦都係必須嘅。
並且我希望西九當局咧係從呢個婚禮嗰個教訓嗰度咧，就睇到個經驗。
有一套公開透明借用場地嘅原則，亦都係必須話到畀公眾聽。那管呢個目標係想揾到收入去達到收支平衡嘅目標，或者係以公眾利益為本，畀公眾參與呢啲目標同細則咧，都應該係好。
透明話到畀公眾聽。咁主席，我咧就希望西九當局咧可以盡快，即係喺租用場地呢度咧，盡快即係同民間大家即係進行一個對話，去完善嗰個規則。另外一樣咧，主席，呢個戲曲中心咧就而家如火如荼啦，即係招標啊、撥款啊各樣。
啊超支啊都係，咁但係嗰個軟件嗰度咧，我哋就睇到。
即係參加呢個誒審批嘅委員會裏邊咧，有誒粵劇界嘅誒誒名人阮兆輝先生，佢係加入咗嗰個委員會。我哋對佢當然好尊重、好有信任，但係大家都知道咧，其實文化界裏邊有好多唔同嘅睇法嘅。噉我哋呢個委員會。
係咪亦都係時間就呢個戲曲中心誒各個設施同埋嗰個使用咧，係應該都進行一個公聽會，就係邀請戲曲誒粵劇界各方面嘅人咧嚟表達個意見，即係透過一個公開嘅場合去將佢哋嘅意見話畀西九管理局聽咧。嗱誒，我哋咧。
咧就喺下嚟緊六月十號咧，就有一個聽藝術界。
嘅會嘅。
月六月十號星期一上午啊，咁咧就而家初定係九點至到十二點啊，噉就驚住早個頭，大家有啲我哋起到身，人哋未起到身啊，咁咧就我哋唉，即係user friendly啲啦，好，咁咧就九點鐘先開始開會。
咁咧就。
誒。
有興趣嘅有意見可以嚟嚟講，但係咧就依個一單一依個誒喺個中心咧，我就唔打算再開公庭會啦，因為以前都開過，而家咧再開就重複，而且如果有真係有格外需要傾嘅咧，可以利用依段時間咧六月十號依個依個機會咧。
都可以表達佢嘅意見嘅，好唔好啊？主席啊，噉我都請秘書咧，即係即係盡量通知翻各界，即係話畀佢哋聽，即係六月嗰個公聽會咧，係歡迎佢哋嚟就各項設施去講自己個睇法咯。
O.K.咁誒，下一位石禮謙。
主席，Mr.林鄭，我唔。
Want you to leave with your team leave here? That we are against you. We are not against. We are we we actually appreciate the professionalism of your team members in trying to do a very difficult job in a very political sensitive area of West Kowloon.
但你try，what we trying to do。The chairman has explained， and you possibly might not understand， that we are here to help。We ensure， we want to make sure that the the governing body of West Kalimantan Authority。
Is doing their job, I'm sure that they are doing it. But it's the job is not to be done by the executive. The executive, I presume, are there to execute the policies, and it's the policies that we have actually questioned.
on the issues of openness, the issues of bylaws, the issues of equality and fairness, the issues of accessibility to each and everyone. Although there have been criticism of wealthy people holding weddings, I hope there will be even more weddings.
在在在在在在西九龍，That everybody can apply on a on the equal footing.
basis on your rules and regulations that you are there to execute a job and doing very well, but you're not here to take the brunt for the failures of the authority not giving us enough information or or their openness of how to.
How they're going to manage this particular important area—that is the crux of today's meeting. And we are not in any way criticising your team. You know, I'm sure you're doing a very good job and a very difficult job.
多謝主席。O K，我諗誒，即係民政局要聽清楚阿石議員講咧，我好贊成佢。即係你作為誒誒總裁，佢個角色，佢唔係可以取代呢個管理局嘅角色嘅。我唔係話佢而家取代緊，而只不過係話佢唔應該做呢啲額外呢啲工作。你個管管理局應該係一個強而有。
努力嘅管理局能夠係喺政策上咧提供好嘅意見，同埋喺監督上咧提出係好有效嘅監督，係嘛？因為如果再係揾一啲噉嘅社會賢達業餘嘅時間去做咧，我哋出好多事。
造成嘅問題，我哋責怪Mr. Lench咧，亦都唔公道。我希望咧，即係民政局要翻去再重新去審視嘅管理局個成員嗰個同埋個組成個方式，好嗎？
即係西九呢一個整體嘅規劃咧嘅計劃咧，所有嘅重大嘅政策咧，都係由管理局去誒決定嘅。咁誒實際執行就由誒行政總裁啊，同埋佢團隊去執執行啦。咁誒，我亦都想回應一句咧，就係誒我誒西九管理局嘅董事局咧，就絕對唔係橡皮圖。
張嚟嘅。
但係我諗你都要加強翻咯，而家你出現這樣那樣問題，你問你即係責怪邊個咧？責怪Mr Lynch佢都頂唔順㗎，係嘛？噉你你應該自己諗下，管理局係冇責任先，呢樣嘢你自己要諗一諗啊，好嘛？你翻去再諗一諗啦，因為議員都講咗好多意見，我諗都係想搞好依件事嘅啫，好冇？
係。
仲冇其他提問，如果冇咧，就六月十號嘅會議係九時正開始嚇。文紀上八誒八時三十分應該係九時正，至到十二時。咁咧就關於兩件事嘅，一件咧就係發展文化軟件，第二件事咧就同依個藝術界嘅溝通同埋合作，好嘛？多謝大家出席。
多謝誒各位。